What virtually everybody finds, including Elon Musk, is
일론 머스크를 포함해 사실상 거의 모두가 깨닫는 것은
the real world is just really, really big
현실 세계가 정말, 정말 크다는 것입니다.
and really, really messy.
그리고 정말, 정말 복잡하다는 것입니다.
The AI thing is so interesting, right? Because
AI는 정말 흥미롭습니다. 왜냐하면
from a technology perspective, it feels like you
기술적 관점에서 보면, 마치
can build products pretty immediately that are going
당장 성공할 제품을
to win.
바로 만들 수 있을 것처럼 느껴지기 때문입니다.
Our entire way of doing everything as humans,
인간으로서 우리가 모든 것을 해온 방식 전체가
we think is going to change. We reinvented
바뀔 것이라고 생각합니다. 우리는
the computer and the new computer is far
컴퓨터를 재발명했고, 새로운 컴퓨터는 훨씬
better than the one that we have been
우리가 지난 50년 정도 동안
building on for the last 50 or so
기반으로 만들어 온 것보다
years.
훨씬 더 낫습니다.
The purpose of building the dominant venture brand
지배적인 벤처 브랜드를 구축한 목적은
was precisely to be able to have the
정확히 말해 회사들이
companies be able to borrow that at the
자신들의 발전 과정에서 가장 결정적인 순간에
most critical points of their development.
그 브랜드를 빌려 쓸 수 있게 하기 위해서였습니다.
So that the companies can kind of use
그래서 회사들이 일종의
our force in the world as a slingshot
우리의 세상에서의 힘을 새총처럼 활용해
to basically build their own force.
본질적으로 자기들만의 힘을 키울 수 있게 하는 겁니다.
You cannot join the firm unless you sign
문화 문서에 서명하지 않으면
the culture document.
우리 회사에 합류할 수 없습니다.
If you had to pick a thing, what
하나를 꼽으라면, 무엇을
are you compounding?
복리로 쌓고 계십니까?
Reputation.
평판입니다.
We have a very special guest, Packy McCormick,
아주 특별한 게스트로 패키 맥코믹을 모셨습니다,
who just wrote an excellent profile of A6
a16z에 대한 훌륭한 프로필을 방금 쓰셨습니다.
and Z. Packy, thanks for coming on the
패키, 팟캐스트에 출연해 주셔서
podcast.
감사합니다.
Thanks for having me.
초대해 주셔서 감사합니다.
Packy, I want to start by saying thank
패키, 먼저 말씀드리고 싶은 것은
you for the amazing piece. Like, it's just
훌륭한 글을 써 주셔서 감사하다는 것입니다. 정말
like incredible. Like, absolutely incredible.
믿기 어려울 정도로 대단했습니다. 정말로 대단했습니다.
So we just really appreciate all the work
그래서 저희는 그 모든 노고에 진심으로 감사드립니다.
that you put into it because that was
그 글에 들이신 작업이 정말
a big one.
큰 작업이었기 때문입니다.
Thank you. I mean, I appreciate being able
감사합니다. 제 말은, 이렇게
to tell the story. It's such a cool
이 이야기를 들려드릴 수 있어서 고맙습니다. 정말 멋진
one. And I appreciate getting to work with
이야기이고, 여러분과 함께
you guys on it.
이 작업을 할 수 있어 감사했습니다.
Everybody, welcome to the Ben and Mark Show,
여러분, '벤 앤드 마크 쇼'에 오신 것을 환영합니다,
first of 2026. And we're now getting into
2026년 첫 회입니다. 이제
how the media ecosystem has changed.
미디어 생태계가 어떻게 바뀌었는지로 들어가겠습니다.
We talked about this great, great Tad Friend
우리는 테드 프렌드가 쓴 정말 훌륭한
profile in The New Yorker in 2015 that
2015년 《뉴요커》 프로필 기사를 이야기했습니다.
I referenced in the piece that I wrote
제가 이번 주 a16z에 쓴 글에서 언급했는데,
on A16Z this past week, saying that that
그것이
kind of kicked off.
어떤 흐름의 출발점이 되었다고 말했습니다.
It was the last kind of point in
그것은 일종의
an era where journalism cared about free speech.
언론이 표현의 자유를 중시하던 시대의 마지막 지점이었습니다.
I think Mark will do a better job
마크가
kind of summarizing what happened over the past
지난 10년 동안 무슨 일이 있었는지
decade.
더 잘 요약해 주실 것 같습니다.
Now we're at the end of that point.
이제 우리는 그 지점의 끝에 와 있습니다.
And I was asking, you know, to what
그리고 저는, 아시다시피,
extent Mark thinks that he and kind of
마크가 자신과
a few people who stood up against this
이에 맞서 일어선 몇몇 사람들이
actually kind of shifted back to this anarchic
실제로 이 무정부적이거나
or liberated view of the press or relationship
해방된 언론관, 또는
with the media that we have now.
우리가 지금 갖고 있는 미디어와의 관계로 되돌리는 데 어느 정도 영향을 미쳤다고 보는지 묻고 있었습니다.
Yeah. And I was just saying, I think
네. 그리고 제가 방금 말씀드린 것은,
you could describe what's happening kind of going
앞으로 벌어질 일을
forward, the information environment being, you know, you
정보 환경의 변화로 보았을 때,
could use kind of three words.
대략 세 단어로 설명할 수 있다는 점입니다.
You could say uncontrolled is maybe the neutral
중립적으로는 '통제되지 않는'이라고 할 수 있고,
word. You could say anarchic is the negative
부정적으로는 '무정부적'이라고 할 수 있으며,
word. You could say liberated is the positive
긍정적으로는 '해방된'이라고 할 수 있습니다.
word, you know, in terms of freedom of
표현의 자유와
speech, freedom of thought, you know, and I
사상의 자유라는 관점에서 말입니다. 그리고 저는
would say at least in the U.S.,
적어도 미국에서는,
I think generally on the Internet.
전반적으로 인터넷에서 그렇다고 생각합니다.
And then, you know, we can talk about
그리고 물론
what other countries are doing, but at least
다른 나라들이 무엇을 하는지도 이야기할 수 있지만, 적어도
in the U.S., you know, we're clearly
미국에서는 분명히
entering a much more free speech world.
훨씬 더 표현의 자유가 큰 세계로 들어가고 있습니다.
So I have to start by saying, like,
그래서 먼저 말씀드려야 할 것은,
I don't think I should claim any moral
여기서 어떤 도덕적
heroism at all here, like at all, because,
영웅주의를 전혀 주장해서는 안 된다고 생각한다는 점입니다. 왜냐하면
you know, I, you know, I mean, I
아시다시피, 저도,
have my own version of my own story
저 나름의 이야기가 있고,
going all the way back to, I turned
그것은 아주 오래전으로 거슬러 올라가는데, 저는
down one of my claims to, I turned
한 번은,
down the opportunity at the time in 1993
1993년에 당시 주어진 기회를 거절한 적이 있습니다.
to implement censorship in the web browser, you
웹 브라우저에 검열을 구현할 기회가 있었는데,
know, which would have been a completely different
아시다시피, 그랬다면 완전히 다른
and, you know, very dystopian world.
그리고 아주 디스토피아적인 세상이었을 겁니다.
So I don't know, maybe I get a
그래서 잘 모르겠지만, 아마 제가
little bit of credit for that. But, you
그 점에서는 약간의 공을 인정받을지도 모르겠습니다만, 그러니까
know, I think for the last decade, like
지난 10년 동안은, 그러니까
I was kind of on the same ride
저도 어느 정도는 같은 흐름을
as everybody else.
모두와 함께 타고 있었던 것 같습니다.
And, you know, we, you know, we, you
그리고 아시다시피, 저희도, 그러니까 저희도
know, I've been on the, I've been on
저는, 저는
the, you know, Facebook board since 2007.
2007년부터 페이스북 이사회에 있었습니다.
So I kind of went through the entire
그래서 저는 그 회사가 겪은
kind of crazy roller coaster that that company
그야말로 미친 듯한 롤러코스터 같은 과정을
went through over the last decade.
지난 10년 동안 전부 함께 겪었습니다.
And then, you know, we've been involved in,
그리고 또 아시다시피, 저희는
you know, lots of these companies.
이런 회사들에 많이 관여해 왔습니다.
You know, I was, you know, I was
아시다시피, 저는, 그러니까 저는
an angel investor in Twitter, angel investor in
트위터의 엔젤 투자자였고, 또
LinkedIn, you know, they both, you know, became
링크드인의 엔젤 투자자였는데, 둘 다, 아시다시피, 어느 시점에는
kind of key parts of the censorship machine
검열 기계의 핵심 부분이 되기도 했습니다.
at certain points.
어떤 시기에는 그렇기도 했습니다.
And so I don't want to claim like
그래서 저는
huge moral heroism.
대단한 도덕적 영웅심을 주장하고 싶지는 않습니다.
I do think a couple of things. One
다만 몇 가지는 그렇게 생각합니다. 하나는
is obviously Elon's purchase of Twitter, you know,
명백히 일론의 트위터 인수가, 아시다시피,
obviously was like a gigantic turning point.
엄청난 전환점이었다는 점입니다.
I also want to give just like enormous
또 저는 정말로 큰
credit to the Substack guys, you know, and
공을 서브스택 사람들에게 돌리고 싶고,
they were very proud because we were the
그들은 매우 자랑스러워했는데, 왜냐하면 저희가
original investor and we're the largest outside investor
초기 투자자였고 외부 투자자 중 가장 큰 투자자였기 때문입니다
in Substack.
서브스택입니다.
And, you know, I think they did a
그리고 아시다시피, 저는 그들이
really, really great job holding the line of
정말, 정말 훌륭하게
freedom of speech under, and I would tell
표현의 자유의 선을 지켜냈다고 생각합니다, 그리고 말씀드리자면
you, under enormous pressure, you know, especially.
엄청난 압박, 특히 그 압박 속에서 말입니다.
And took a very consistent and totally principled
그리고 매우 일관되게, 완전히 원칙적인
stand on it.
입장을 취했습니다.
Yeah, that's right. And they got, I don't
네, 맞습니다. 그리고 그들은, 저는
know if people remember this or not, but
사람들이 기억하는지 모르겠지만,
I mean, they got really lit up, you
정말로 엄청나게 공격을 받았습니다, 그러니까
know, by a lot of the sort of,
그런 종류의 많은
you know, anti-speech forces for, you know,
표현을 반대하는 세력들로부터, 그러니까
I mean, the whole litany of, you know,
그러니까 그 흔한
kind of standard accusations of just being absolutely
그러니까 흔히 나오는 상투적인 비난 목록 전체를, 완전히
horrible.
끔찍하다는 식으로 말입니다.
And yeah, they stuck to their principles the
그리고 네, 그들은 원칙을
whole time. And then they, you know, you
끝까지 지켰습니다. 그리고 또, 그러니까
know, at least with Elon, it acts like
적어도 일론의 경우에는, 그는
he's Elon.
그가 일론답게 행동합니다.
And so when he wants to go to
그래서 그가
war with like, you know, somebody who's like
그러니까, 더 검열하라고 요구하는
trying to get him to censor more, like
어떤 사람과 맞서 싸우고 싶어지면,
he does it in a very kind of
그는 아주
forced, you know, public visible and forceful way.
노골적이고 공개적으로 보이는, 그리고 강력한 방식으로 합니다.
You know, the Substack, you know, Substack's still,
아시다시피 서브스택은, 그러니까 서브스택은 아직
you know, a younger company. And so they
더 젊은 회사입니다. 그래서 그들은
don't have that level of kind of just
그 정도로
throw weight in the world yet.
세상에 영향력을 행사할 수준은 아직 없습니다.
And so they have the harder version of
그래서 그들은
the challenge and they had to fight, you
더 어려운 형태의 도전을 안고 있고, 또
know, a whole bunch of fights, including, you
여러 싸움을 해야 했습니다, 그러니까
know, fights that aren't even public, you know,
심지어 공개되지도 않는 싸움들까지도요,
to basically keep the service with high integrity.
기본적으로 서비스를 높은 무결성으로 유지하기 위해서입니다.
So I think a good place to kind
그래서 저는
of talk about a bunch of the themes
저희가 글에서 다룬 여러 주제를
that we covered in the piece, one of
이야기하기 좋은 지점이 여기라고 생각하는데, 그중 하나가
which is, I mean, the Substack investment.
즉, 서브스택 투자입니다.
I remember at the time I was on
당시 저는
Substack, my career was starting because of Substack,
서브스택에 있었고, 제 커리어는 서브스택 덕분에 시작됐으며,
and I still at the time thought it
그때도 저는
was kind of a crazy investment.
그게 좀 미친 투자라고 생각했습니다.
Were you thinking about it from the perspective
당신은 그걸 어떤 관점에서 생각하셨나요
of this is going to be a great
이게 훌륭한
returner, this is something that is good for
수익을 가져다줄 것이라는 것과, 미래에
the future?
좋은 것이라는 것 중에서요?
Is it a mix of the two of
둘의 혼합인가요,
those things? And then to what extent have
그리고 또 어느 정도까지
you allowed Substack to fight that fight by
당신이 서브스택 편에 서서
being on their side that they wouldn't have
서브스택이
been able to do if you weren't there?
당신이 없었다면 하지 못했을 그 싸움을 할 수 있게 해주셨나요?
Yeah, so, you know, we never make it,
네, 그래서 아시다시피, 저희는
you know, we never make investments for just
순전히
purely kind of social and political reasons.
사회적·정치적 이유만으로 투자를 하지는 않습니다.
Like, so, you know, the goal, obviously, always
그러니까 목표는, 당연히 언제나
as sort of fiduciaries is to generate returns.
수탁자로서 수익을 만들어내는 것입니다.
And so, you know, in the main business.
그리고 그게 저희 본업입니다.
And so, you know, we always invest with
그래서 아시다시피, 저희는 항상
the intention that the company that we invest
저희가 투자하는 회사가
in, you know, has the opportunity to become
아시다시피, 어떤 존재가 될 기회를 갖도록 한다는 의도로요,
what we call kind of a cornerstone franchise,
저희가 이른바 핵심 축이 되는 프랜차이즈라고 부르는 존재가 되는 것이요,
you know, in the industry and an important
아시다시피 업계에서, 그리고 중요한
force in the world.
세계적 영향력이 되기 위해서입니다.
And, you know, we certainly believe that as
그리고 아시다시피, 저희는 확실히 그렇게 믿었습니다,
Substack at the time. And, you know, we
당시 Substack에 대해서요. 그리고 아시다시피 저희는
believe that more than ever today. So I
오늘날 그 어느 때보다도 더 그렇게 믿고 있습니다. 그래서 저는
think that's true.
그게 사실이라고 생각합니다.
But I also think, you know, I think
하지만 저는 또 아시다시피, 저는
this is kind of the magic in a
이것이 일종의 마법이라고 생각합니다,
lot of what we do, you know, in
우리가 하는 많은 일에서요, 아시다시피,
Silicon Valley, which is I think the companies
실리콘밸리에서 말인데, 제 생각에는 기업들이
in many, not in every case, but in
많은 경우에, 모든 경우는 아니지만,
many cases, the companies that become the best
많은 경우에, 자기들의 최선의
version of themselves also become the most successful
모습이 되는 기업들이 또한 가장 성공적인
businesses.
사업이 됩니다.
And I think Substack is a great example
그리고 Substack은 그 훌륭한 사례라고 생각합니다.
of that. And Substack is actually a very,
그것의요. 그리고 Substack은 사실 매우,
very, very good example of that, because if
정말로 정말 좋은 사례인데, 왜냐하면 만약
Substack is making its writers successful, then it's
Substack이 자사 작가들을 성공하게 만든다면, 그것은
making itself successful.
자기 자신을 성공하게 만드는 것이기 때문입니다.
Right. And so it's got this just like
맞습니다. 그래서 이것은 마치
extremely direct alignment of interest between its success
자사의 성공과
and its writers success. And then as a
작가들의 성공 사이에 매우 직접적인 이해관계의 정렬이 있습니다. 그리고 그 결과
consequence of that, if its writers are successful,
그로 인해, 만약 작가들이 성공한다면,
kind of by definition, you know, those writers,
어떤 의미에서는 정의상, 아시다시피, 그 작가들의
you know, readers are successful. They're getting what
아시다시피, 독자들도 만족합니다. 그들은
they want.
원하는 것을 얻고 있습니다.
And so, you know, I would say, you
그래서, 아시다시피, 저는 말씀드리고 싶습니다,
know, there were sort of a bunch of
아시다시피, 우리가 Substack에 투자한 데에는
reasons we invested in Substack. You know, one
여러 가지 이유가 있었습니다. 아시다시피, 하나는
was just, you know, we fell in love
그냥 아시다시피, 우리는 그 사람들과
with the guys.
사랑에 빠졌습니다.
And, you know, you probably know the guys
그리고 아시다시피, 당신도 아마 그 사람들을 아시겠지만
they're easy to fall in love with. So
쉽게 사랑에 빠지게 되는 사람들입니다. 그래서
that was the that was the easy part.
그건 쉬운 부분이었습니다.
And then, you know, look, I had been
그리고 아시다시피, 보세요, 저는
around, you know, we had been around, you
오래전부터, 아시다시피, 우리는 오래전부터,
know, you know, the web going all the
아시다시피, 웹이 처음 시작되었을 때부터
way back and then, you know, particularly the,
계속 지켜봐 왔고, 그리고 아시다시피, 특히
you know, the kind of golden age of
아시다시피, 블로깅의
blogging, you know, was kind of this kind
황금기라고 할 수 있는 시기는
of very, you know, special time.
아주 특별한 시간이었습니다.
And, you know, you know, and blogging really,
그리고 아시다시피, 블로깅은 정말로,
you know, I think, you know, maybe gets
아시다시피, 제 생각에는, 아시다시피, 아마도
underestimated because maybe there was no single company
과소평가되었을 수 있습니다. 왜냐하면 아마도 이에 대해
that kind of got full credit for it
완전한 공로를 인정받은 단일 회사가
or something.
없었기 때문일 겁니다.
But, you know, it really created the phenomenon
하지만 아시다시피, 블로깅 현상은 정말로
of blogging created an enormous amount of intellectual
엄청난 양의 지적 콘텐츠를
content, you know, that basically was not going
만들어냈습니다. 아시다시피, 그것은 기본적으로
to exist otherwise.
그렇지 않았다면 존재하지 않았을 것입니다.
And then it just, you know, blogging kind
그리고 나서, 아시다시피, 블로깅은
of just always had a series of problems
항상 일련의 문제들이 있었습니다.
because there was no single company behind it.
왜냐하면 그 뒤에 단일 회사가 없었기 때문입니다.
But, you know, one of the problems was
하지만 아시다시피, 문제 중 하나는
bloggers just could it's very hard for bloggers
블로거들이 돈을 벌기가
to make money. Right.
매우 어려웠습니다. 맞죠.
And so, you know, the Substack guys basically
그래서 아시다시피, Substack 팀은 기본적으로
said, well, we're, you know, we're going to
우리가 그걸 할 거라고 말했습니다,
do that. But, you know, we solved the
아시다시피. 하지만 우리가 경제 모델을
economic model.
해결했습니다.
People are ready to pay now for content.
사람들은 이제 콘텐츠에 돈을 지불할 준비가 되어 있습니다.
And this makes sense.
그리고 이건 말이 됩니다.
And then, you know, there was this chicken
그리고 아시다시피, 처음부터 이런
and egg thing right up front, which was
닭이 먼저냐 달걀이 먼저냐 하는 문제가 있었는데,
like, well, you know, can you really see
음, 아시다시피, 정말로 볼 수 있느냐,
that, you know, the Internet's a wash with
아시다시피, 인터넷은 콘텐츠로
content.
넘쳐납니다.
People aren't paying for almost any of it.
사람들은 거의 대부분에 돈을 내지 않습니다.
Like, are they really going to, you know,
정말로 사람들이, 아시다시피,
you have to kind of squint and kind
좀 눈을 가늘게 뜨고
of say, OK, are people actually going to
좋아, 사람들이 정말로
pay for any of the stuff that they're
지금 무료로 받고 있는 것들에 대해
getting today?
돈을 낼까요?
And I think the thing that in that
그리고 제 생각에 그 경우에
case that we were that we had faith
우리가 믿었던 것은
in was basically this could be what we
기본적으로 이것이 우리가
call a supply driven market, which is, right,
공급 주도 시장이라고 부르는 것이 될 수 있다는 것이었습니다.
if you provide the monetization capability,
만약 수익화 기능을 제공한다면,
then you're going to bring into existence writers
그러면 오늘날 존재하지 않는 작가들과
and content that don't exist today.
콘텐츠를 탄생시킬 수 있습니다.
And that is the way to create new
그리고 그것이 오늘날 보이지 않는
demand that's not visible today. And then that
새로운 수요를 창출하는 방법입니다. 그리고 나서 그
demand is going to come back around and
수요가 다시 돌아와서
is going to incent more writers and more
더 많은 작가들과 더 많은 콘텐츠에
content.
인센티브를 줄 것입니다.
And so it was basically a bet that
그래서 이것은 기본적으로
there's like an entire generation of high quality
수익화 메커니즘이 존재하지 않기 때문에
content that doesn't exist because the monetization mechanism
존재하지 않는 고품질 콘텐츠의
doesn't exist.
한 세대 전체가 있다는 베팅이었습니다.
And that's, you know, that's certainly what Chris
그리고 그게, 아시다시피, Chris와
and his partners believe. And I think that's
그리고 그의 파트너들도 그렇게 믿습니다. 그리고 저는 그게
that's absolutely what's proven out.
그렇게 되는 게 실제로 완전히 입증됐다고 생각합니다.
And so, yeah, I think it's like a
그래서 네, 제 생각에는 이게
great example of founders that like really see
아직 존재하지 않는 미래를 정말로 내다보는 창업자들의
a future that doesn't exist yet.
훌륭한 사례라고 생각합니다.
And it's obvious to them. And unfortunately, in
그들에게는 그게 너무도 자명합니다. 그리고 안타깝게도,
that case, they were able to, you know,
그 경우에는 그들이, 아시다시피,
convince us.
저희를 설득해냈습니다.
Whenever we really screw up, it's because there's
저희가 정말 크게 실수할 때는, 미래를 내다보는 창업자가 있고
a founder who can see the future and
그 사람이 찾아와서
they come and they sit in our office.
저희 사무실에 앉아
They tell us what the future is and
미래가 어떤 모습인지 들려주는데,
we say, yeah, I don't really buy it.
저희가 “네, 저는 잘 믿기 어렵네요”라고 말하기 때문입니다.
Right.
그렇죠.
And then for the next 30 years, you
그리고 그다음 30년 동안
know, we have to read about the, you
저희는, 아시다시피,
know, glorious success of this thing as that
그 미래가 실제로 전개되는 동안
future actually develops.
그것의 엄청난 성공담을 읽어야 합니다.
And like that really sucks. And I don't
그건 정말 괴롭습니다. 그리고 저는
like to talk about those.
그런 얘기는 별로 하고 싶지 않습니다.
But I will say, you know, Substack is,
하지만 말씀드리자면, 서브스택은
you know, maybe they're just really good at
어쩌면 그들이 영업을 정말 잘하는 것일 수도 있지만,
sales, but they fully convinced us.
저희를 완전히 설득했습니다.
And I'm really thrilled that that's what's happening.
그래서 지금 그런 일이 벌어지고 있는 게 정말 기쁩니다.
They were kind of ahead of the the
그들은 다소 앞서서
kind of change from old media to new
구미디어에서 뉴미디어로의
media in that, you know, as the brand
변화를 포착했습니다. 즉, 브랜드가
moved from The New York Times or The
뉴욕타임스나
Wall Street Journal to the actual writers themselves,
월스트리트저널에서 실제로는 작가 개인에게로 이동하면서,
Substack was like a massive enabler for that.
서브스택이 그 변화를 가능하게 한 거대한 촉매 역할을 했습니다.
And, you know, they created this thing which
그리고 그들은
they call the non-fungible writer, which is,
“대체 불가능한 작가”라고 부르는 개념을 만들었는데,
you know, like how many things in the
아시다시피 신문에 실리는 것들 중
newspaper could anybody write?
누구나 쓸 수 있는 게 얼마나 많습니까?
And including AI, by the way. And, you
참고로 AI도 포함해서요. 그리고
know, how much is like truly like interesting
그중에서 정말로 흥미롭고
and valuable.
가치 있는 것이 얼마나 되는가라는 질문입니다.
And they really wanted all the truly interesting
그들은 정말로 흥미롭고
and valuable things to be able to build
가치 있는 것들이
their people, to build their own brands and
사람들이 자기 브랜드와
their own businesses on Substack.
자기 비즈니스를 서브스택에서 구축할 수 있도록 하길 원했습니다.
And that that would that that also turned
그리고 그것이, 그 또한,
out to be very true.
결과적으로 완전히 사실로 드러났습니다.
Yeah. And that was where, you know, Hamish
네. 그리고 그 지점에서, 아시다시피, 특히 해미시가
in particular, right, turned out to be really
그들의 팀에서 정말로
critical on their team, you know, and, you
핵심적인 역할을 했던 것으로 드러났고요. 그리고
know, he and I had a conversation early
저와 그가 초기에
on this where, you know, I was like,
이 주제로 대화를 나눴을 때 저는
well, you know, I don't know, are these
“글쎄요, 이 사람들이 과연”
people ever going to leave their publications?
자기 매체를 떠날까요?
Are they ever going to actually write content
정말로 콘텐츠를
that's that, you know, like, you know, when
직접 쓰게 될까요?”라고 했습니다. 서브스택이
Substack was gearing up, it's when, in my
준비되던 시기가, 제 관점에서는
view, the press kind of became this kind
언론이 일종의
of extreme and negative monoculture.
극단적이고 부정적인 단일 문화로 변해가던 때였습니다.
And so I was like, all right, you've
그래서 저는 “좋아요, 그러면”이라고 했죠.
got, you know, because he's like, you've got
왜냐하면 그가 “당신은 이렇게 말하잖아요,”
all these writers kind of trapped at these
즉 “이런 곳들에 작가들이 갇혀 있다”고요.
places.
라고 했기 때문입니다.
And I'm like, well, are they really trapped?
그런데 저는 “정말로 갇혀 있는 건가요?”라고 물었습니다.
Like, are they, you know, are they in
그러니까, 아시다시피, 감옥에 있는 건가요,
jail or have they built the jail? Like,
아니면 스스로 감옥을 만든 건가요?
you know, like, and if they leave, are
그리고 만약 그들이 떠난다면,
they going to be any different?
과연 뭐가 달라지겠습니까?
Right. And he's like, look, if their only
그렇죠. 그러자 그는 “보세요, 만약 먹고살기 위한 유일한 선택지가
option to basically put food on the table
사실상 먹고살기 위해서
is to work for a publication that basically,
어떤 매체에서 일하는 것뿐이라면,”
you know, requires them to write a certain
그 매체가 일정한 방식으로 쓰기를 요구할 때
way, then they're going to write that way,
그들은 그렇게 쓸 수밖에 없습니다,
you know, because they need to pay the
왜냐하면 생활비를
bills.
내야 하기 때문입니다.
But he said, he basically said, I guarantee
하지만 그는 “제가 장담하는데
you that there's a lot of these folks,
이들 중에는 그런 사람들이 많습니다.”라고 말했습니다.
you know, where if they had an independent
즉, 만약 그들에게 독립적인
path, they would take, you know, they would
길이 있다면 그 길을 택할 것이고,
be thrilled to be able to, you know,
정말로 기쁘게
maybe break themselves out of jail.
스스로 감옥에서 빠져나오려 할 것입니다.
And they would be thrilled to, you know,
그리고 그들은 정말로 기쁘게
write about things, you know, from different angles
여러 사안을 다른 관점에서 쓰게 될 것입니다.
and have different tastes on things.
그리고 취향도 달라질 것입니다.
And, you know, you'd see this basically, you
그리고 결국, 아시다시피,
know, this liberation phenomenon take place where you'd
일종의 해방 현상이 일어나서
have actually many different kinds of voices even
실제로 아주 다양한 목소리가
coming from people where you wouldn't expect it
원래의 작업만 보고는 기대하지 못했던 사람들에게서도
based on the work that they did for,
나오게 될 것이고,
you know, the New York Times or whoever.
뉴욕타임스든 어디든 그들이 했던 일과는 다르게 말이죠.
And, of course, he was 100% right.
그리고 물론 그는 100% 옳았습니다.
You can see a world where because it
이런 그림도 그려볼 수 있습니다. 그것이
attracts kind of all of the best writers
최고의 작가들을 전부 끌어모으는 것 같습니다.
from all of these different places who can
이런저런 다양한 곳에서, 자기 사업을
build their own businesses, Substack becomes 10 times
직접 만들 수 있는 사람들이 모이면서 Substack은 10배
larger than any of the media organizations that
어떤 미디어 조직보다도 더
are places.
커지게 됩니다.
I love the email that you sent to
당신이 보낸 이메일이 정말 좋았는데요.
Ali at Databricks, Ben, where you talk about
Databricks의 Ali에게 보낸 것 말입니다, 벤, 거기서 당신은
the fact that, you know, the business was
그러니까, 사업이 사실은
underselling itself.
스스로를 너무 낮게 평가하고 있었다는 점을요.
He was underselling the business and it was
그는 그 사업을 과소평가하고 있었고, 그것은
going to be 10 times bigger than Oracle.
오라클보다 10배 더 커질 거였습니다.
So $2 trillion.
그러면 2조 달러죠.
Yeah.
네.
I want to understand like the mechanism of
저는 그 메커니즘이 무엇인지
that.
이해하고 싶습니다.
Like, do you think that happens every generation
즉, 매 세대마다 그런 일이 일어난다고 보십니까,
that the new companies are 10 times bigger?
새 회사들이 10배 더 커지는 일이요?
Why does that happen?
왜 그런 일이 일어날까요?
Is it just software?
그냥 소프트웨어 때문인가요?
Yeah.
네.
So on that one, it was actually pretty
그 부분은 사실 꽤
simple because if you compared the on-premise
단순한데, 온프레미스
software companies to the cloud,
소프트웨어 회사들을 클라우드와,
software companies, so compare PeopleSoft to Workday or
클라우드 소프트웨어 회사들과 비교하면, PeopleSoft와 Workday를 비교하거나
compare Siebel Software to Salesforce, the cloud version
Siebel Software와 Salesforce를 비교할 때, 클라우드 버전은
was just 10 times bigger.
그냥 10배 더 컸습니다.
And Oracle was kind of the on-premise
그리고 오라클은 일종의 온프레미스
version of Databricks.
Databricks의 버전 같은 존재였죠.
You know, kind of, you know, rough analog,
그러니까, 대략적인 비유로 말하면요,
you know, things are different.
물론 상황은 다릅니다.
You know, data is bigger and so forth.
데이터가 더 크고, 그런 것들이 있죠.
But if you look at like who is
하지만 클라우드에서 누가
going to be the data kind of provider
데이터 제공자가 될지,
in the cloud, the provider of technology to
즉 클라우드에서 기술을 제공해서
manage your data in the cloud, it was
클라우드에서 당신의 데이터를 관리하게 해줄 제공자가 누구인지 보면, 그건
going to, I mean, I was very confident
10배로 커질 거였고, 그러니까 저는 매우 확신했는데
Databricks would win that.
Databricks가 그걸 이길 거라고요.
And so then if you say, well, what's
그러면 '그 시장 규모가
the market size of that?
얼마냐'고 말할 수 있겠죠.
And by the way, you know, when I
그리고 참고로, 제가
said that AI wasn't as big as it
AI가 지금만큼 크지 않을 거라고
is, so I think that that's helping my
말했었는데, 그래서 그게 제
prediction.
예측에 도움이 된 것 같습니다.
But, you know, like it was just clearly
하지만, 그건 그냥 분명히
going to be 10 times bigger.
10배 더 커질 일이었습니다.
And I was like, Ali, why are you
그래서 저는 'Ali, 왜 당신은
trying to convince this candidate that you're going
이 후보자에게 우리가
to be worth $10 billion?
100억 달러 가치가 될 거라고 설득하려 하냐'고 했죠.
Like that's the, what are you even talking
그게 뭐, 도대체 무슨 말을
about?
하는 겁니까?
But, you know, Ali is super paranoid.
하지만 Ali는 굉장히 편집증적입니다.
So, you know, God bless him.
그러니, 뭐, 신의 가호가 있기를 바랍니다.
So, you know, those are kinds of things.
그래서 그런 종류의 일들이 있습니다.
And like, you have to know your entrepreneur.
그리고 당신은 창업자를 잘 알아야 합니다.
I mean, I think this is, you know,
제 말은, 저는 이것이,
one of the things that I think Mark
제가 Marc가
does very well is like, you know, that
매우 잘하는 것 중 하나라고 생각하는데, 즉
advice isn't advice you give to every entrepreneur.
그 조언은 모든 창업자에게 하는 조언이 아닙니다.
It's, you know, it was very worked well
즉, 그것은 그에게는
specifically for him.
특히 매우 잘 통했습니다.
And I think that, you know, that's always
그리고 저는 그런 일이
the case.
늘 그렇다고 생각합니다.
Like it's a very psychological game running a
회사를 운영하는 것은 매우 심리적인
company.
게임입니다.
And so you have to kind of tap
그래서 어느 정도는 그 사람의
in to that person's particular psychology to kind
고유한 심리에 맞춰
of change the trajectory of what the company
회사가 하는 일의 진행 궤적을
is doing into the right direction.
올바른 방향으로 바꿔야 합니다.
And I'd also add, you know, back to
또 한 가지 덧붙이자면, Substack 얘기로 돌아가서,
you on the Substack point, like I think
저는 Substack이
Substack could be like a thousand times the
기존 콘텐츠 산업의
size of the existing like content industry, whatever
규모가 어떻든 간에,
you want to call it, media news industry,
즉 미디어·뉴스 산업의
the collective, you know, kind of value.
전체 가치보다도 천 배는 더 커질 수 있다고 봅니다.
And the reason is because, and, you know,
그 이유는,
you're an example of this yourself.
당신이 바로 그 사례이기 때문입니다.
So, you know, my whole life, so I'm
저는 제 평생을 보면
like, you know, mid fifties.
대략 50대 중반입니다.
And so like I grew up, you know,
저는 자라면서,
when I was a kid and teenager, you
제가 아이였고 십대였을 때,
know, the moral panic of the era was
그 시대의 도덕적 공황은
television.
텔레비전이었습니다.
And it was just this like endless litany
그리고 그것은 끝없는 나열이었고,
of sort of social criticism, you know, from
일종의 사회적 비판의 연속이었으며,
kind of, you know, fancy people basically saying,
소위 점잖은 사람들이 기본적으로 말하길,
you know, consumers are, you know, basically normal
소비자들은, 즉 기본적으로 평범한
people are idiots.
사람들은 멍청하다고 했습니다.
They just want to sit in front of
그들은 그저 앞에 앉아서
the boob tube.
바보상자를 보고 싶어 한다는 겁니다.
They just want to like be couch potatoes.
그들은 그저 소파에 붙어 있는 인간이 되고 싶어 한다는 것입니다.
You know, the line everybody used at the
당시에 모두가 쓰던 말은,
time was Americans watch six hours of TV
미국인들은 하루에 TV를 6시간 본다는 말이었습니다.
a day.
하루에 말입니다.
And then you turned on TV and you
그리고 TV를 켜면,
just saw this, they have this term, the
그저 'vast wasteland'라는 표현이 떠오르는,
vast wasteland of, you know, game shows and
퀴즈쇼 같은 오락 프로그램과
bullshit.
온갖 헛소리로 가득한 '광대한 황무지'였습니다.
And it was just like this, like very
그리고 그것은 정말로, 아주
dystopian kind of thing of just like people
디스토피아적인 느낌이었고, 사람들이 그저
are just morons.
완전히 바보들이라는 식이었습니다.
And then, you know, the internet version of
그리고 이제 그 인터넷판은
that is, of course, you know, that kind
물론 그런 종류의
of moral panic is transferred straight over onto
도덕적 공황이 그대로
the internet in the form of, you know,
인터넷으로 옮겨가,
of course, you know, short form videos, TikTok.
짧은 영상, 틱톡 같은 형태로 나타납니다.
You know, people just want to watch, you
그러니까 사람들은 그저
know, these stupid short form videos.
이런 멍청한 짧은 영상만 보고 싶어 한다는 식입니다.
And it's just playing the piano is the
처음에는 '피아노 치기'가
original one, right?
원조였던 셈입니다, 그렇지 않습니까.
Yeah, exactly.
네, 맞습니다.
Cat videos.
고양이 영상입니다.
By the way, I'm an aficionado of cat
참고로 저는 고양이 영상 마니아입니다.
videos.
고양이 영상을 좋아합니다.
I do not look down on cat videos
저는 고양이 영상을
whatsoever.
전혀 폄하하지 않습니다.
AI cat videos are my current favorite genre
요즘 제가 가장 좋아하는 장르는 AI 고양이 영상이며
of any form of entertainment.
어떤 오락보다도 가장 좋아하는 장르입니다.
So I will.
그러니 저는 앞으로도 그렇게 하겠습니다.
The AI cat videos are very good.
AI 고양이 영상은 정말 훌륭합니다.
I will.
저는
Yes, Ben can confirm.
계속 그러겠습니다.
I send her out a lot of AI
제가 벤에게 AI 고양이 영상을
cat videos.
많이 보내드리기 때문입니다.
However, there is an enormous market for just
하지만 그냥 대중 매체를 위한 거대한 시장이 있습니다,
like mass media, just for like whatever, you
그러니까 무엇이든 대중적인
know, for whatever game shows or sitcoms or,
게임쇼나 시트콤 같은 것들, 또는
you know, soap operas or their modern versions
연속극이나 그 현대판 같은 것들을 위한
of those.
시장이 존재한다는 뜻입니다.
And there's a giant, you know, mass media
그리고 대중 매체에는
market for cat videos.
고양이 영상을 위한 거대한 시장도 있습니다.
But this goes back to this idea of
하지만 이는 다시
supply driven market.
공급 주도 시장이라는 생각으로 돌아갑니다.
There's also, I think, just like enormous latent
또한 저는 잠재적으로
demand for actual smart, high quality stuff and
정말 똑똑하고 고품질인 콘텐츠에 대한 수요가 매우 크다고 봅니다.
particularly in media and in every kind of
특히 미디어에서, 그리고 모든 종류의
media.
미디어 전반에서 그렇습니다.
And I think the issue is not lack
그리고 문제는 수요 부족이
of demand.
아니라고 생각합니다.
I think the issue is lack of supply.
문제는 공급 부족이라고 생각합니다.
Because like this goes back to, you know,
왜냐하면 이는
kind of consumer marketing 101, which is consumer
소비자 마케팅의 기본으로 돌아가는데,
people don't know what they want until it's
소비자들은 무엇을 원하는지
given to them.
그것이 주어지기 전까지는 알지 못합니다.
Right.
그렇습니다.
You know, nobody ever asked for a Macintosh.
예를 들어 아무도 매킨토시를
Nobody ever asked for an iPhone.
원한다고 요청한 적은 없습니다.
Like, you know, these things had to be
이런 것들은 먼저
designed and built, you know, provided on the
설계되고 만들어져서, 공급 측에서 제공되어야
supply side before the demand materialized.
수요가 생깁니다.
And then the demand, of course, turned out
그러고 나면 수요는, 당연히,
to be, you know, far higher than anybody
누구도
expected.
예상하지 못한 수준으로 훨씬 더 커졌습니다.
And I think that that same thing is
그리고 저는 이런 일이
exactly true of media.
미디어에서도 정확히 똑같이 적용된다고 봅니다.
I think a great early existence proof of
이에 대한 초기의 훌륭한 실증 사례로는
this was the success of long form podcasting,
장시간 팟캐스트의 성공이 있습니다.
you know, which is I remember my early
저는 초기에
conversations with some of the early long form
장시간 팟캐스터 몇 분과 나눈
podcasters.
대화를 기억합니다.
And they're like, it's the strangest thing we've
그분들이 그러더군요, 우리가 본 것 중 가장 이상한 일이라고 했습니다.
ever seen because everybody tells us that the
왜냐하면 모두가 소비자들은
consumers have short attention spans.
주의 집중 시간이 짧다고 말하기 때문이라는 것입니다.
But, you know, people are literally watching three
그런데 실제로 사람들은
hour podcasts and we get the analytics and
3시간짜리 팟캐스트를 보고, 저희가 분석을 보면
people are watching all the way to the
사람들이 끝까지
end of the three hour podcast.
3시간짜리를 전부 시청한다는 것입니다.
And so I view this very much as
그래서 저는 이것을
like, you know, this is one of these
전형적인
classic markets that's a barbell, which is, yeah,
바벨형 시장 중 하나로 봅니다, 즉 한쪽에는
you have a certain amount of whatever, just,
한쪽에는 어느 정도의, 그저
you know, whatever, you know, mainstream, you know,
주류적인, 대중적인
sort of mainstream, whatever, you know, filler or
필러 콘텐츠 같은 것이
whatever on the one side.
존재합니다.
But you have this massive sort of untapped
하지만 엄청나게, 아직 미개척된
market for high quality content and basically every
고품질 콘텐츠에 대한 시장이 거의 모든
domain.
분야에 존재합니다.
And they're just, you know, technological transformation, the
그리고, 그러니까, 기술적 변혁으로 인해,
existing structure of the media company was a
기존 미디어 기업의 구조는
structure that was designed for a world of
어떤 세계를 위해 설계된
centralized media.
구조였습니다, 즉 중앙집중형 미디어의 세계를 위한 것이었습니다.
You need, you need a new structure today.
오늘날에는 새로운 구조가 필요합니다.
And, you know, of course, that's, you know,
그리고 물론, 그러니까, 그게 바로
that's why we're so high on Substack.
저희가 Substack을 그렇게 높게 평가하는 이유입니다.
But yeah, when we look at Substack, it's
그런데 Substack을 보면, 이것은
the exact same thing that you were just
방금 당신이
talking about with Databricks, which is like, wow,
Databricks에 대해 말한 것과 완전히 같은데, 와,
this thing could be orders of magnitude,
이건 규모가 자릿수 단위로,
orders of magnitude multiples larger, you know, than
지금까지 본 어떤 것보다 자릿수 배로 더 클 수 있습니다,
anything we've seen so far.
지금까지 본 어떤 것보다 훨씬 더 큽니다.
And, you know, frankly, I think we're starting
그리고 솔직히 말해서, 저는 저희가 이제
to see that implicit in kind of the
그게 암묵적으로
fund sizes that you raise is some kind
당신들이 조성하는 펀드 규모에 담겨 있는 것을
of view on how big the future is
미래가 얼마나 큰지에 대한 관점으로
going to be
보기 시작했다고 생각합니다.
or how much of the world technology is
또는 앞으로 10년 동안 기술이
going to eat over the next decade or
세상에서 얼마나 많은 부분을
so.
집어삼킬지에 관한 이야기입니다.
What does 15 billion say about kind of
150억 달러는
what the world looks like in a decade
10년 뒤 세상이 어떤 모습일지를
and how many substacks there are that are
그리고 자신들이 대체하는 대상보다 훨씬 더 큰 Substack이
much bigger than whoever they're replacing?
얼마나 많을지를, 150억 달러는 무엇이라고 말해 줍니까?
Well, I think that we reinvented the computer.
저는 우리가 컴퓨터를 재발명했다고 생각합니다.
So and the new computer is far better
그리고 그 새로운 컴퓨터는 훨씬 더 뛰어나며
than the one that we have been kind
우리가 그동안
of building on for the last 50 or
지난 50년 정도
so years.
의존해 온 것보다 낫습니다.
Well, really longer than that, but 50 in
사실 그보다 더 오래지만, 본격적으로는 50년입니다.
earnest. And, you know, so there is that
그렇습니다. 그래서 그런 측면이 있습니다.
I mean, we talk about this all the
그러니까, 저희는 이 이야기를
time in the firm.
회사에서 늘 합니다.
And there's not a problem that we can
그리고 저희가 생각하기에
think of that you can't that you won't
AI로 해결하지 못할 문제는
be able to solve with A.I.
앞으로 없을 것 같습니다.
So like almost every problem in the world
즉 세상의 거의 모든 문제를
and you, you know, from cancer to transportation,
예를 들어 암부터 교통까지,
transportation to massive fraud in the U.S.,
교통에서 미국의 대규모 사기까지,
you just name a problem in the headlines.
헤드라인에 나오는 문제를 하나만 꼽아보십시오.
And we're like, oh, yeah, we can solve
그러면 저희는 "아, 네, 그건 해결할 수 있습니다"라고 말합니다.
that. And so it's kind of the reinvention
말합니다. 그래서 이것은 일종의 재발명이며
of everything.
모든 것을 다시 만드는 일입니다.
So like all our our entire way of
그러니까 인간으로서 우리가
doing everything as humans, we think is going
모든 일을 해오던 방식 전체가
to change.
바뀔 것이라고 생각합니다.
And so, you know, I would view it
그래서 저는 이것을
as 15 billion to start for us because
저희에게는 150억 달러가 시작에 불과하다고 보는데,
there's so much to do and there's so
할 일이 너무 많고,
many things that are going to get built.
만들어질 것들이 너무 많기 때문입니다.
And, you know, like some of it is
그리고 그중 일부는
just timing with the entrepreneurs, but we think
기업가들과의 타이밍 문제일 뿐이지만, 저희는
the number of entrepreneurs is going to multiply
기업가의 수 자체도 기하급수적으로 늘 것이라고
as well, because the kind of the the
생각합니다. 왜냐하면
ease of going from an idea to a
아이디어에서
really fantastic solution and a fantastic product is
정말 훌륭한 해결책과 훌륭한 제품으로 가는 과정이
just going to be so much simpler.
훨씬 더 단순해질 것이기 때문입니다.
Because, you know, one of the things that
왜냐하면 AI가 특히 잘하는 것 중 하나가
A.I. is best at, of course, is
AI가 가장 잘하는 건, 물론,
kind of building stuff. And and so, yeah,
뭔가를 만들어내는 데 가장 뛰어나기 때문입니다. 그래서, 네,
it's just a very unique time in kind
지금은 그냥 정말 아주 독특한 시기인 것 같고
of the history of the world.
세계 역사 속에서 말입니다.
Yeah. Yeah. The audio body experience I have
네, 네. 제가 AI와 정기적으로 겪는 유체이탈 같은 경험은
with the A.I. on a regular basis
AI를 일상적으로 사용하다 보면,
now is, you know, it's like, OK, I
요즘은, 그러니까, '좋습니다, 저는'
think about the way Ben does and then
벤이 생각하는 방식으로 생각해 보고,
I'm like, all right, how might you apply
그리고 '좋습니다, 그럼 어떻게 적용할 수 있지
A.I. to solve?
AI로 이걸 해결하려면?'이라고 합니다.
Yeah. For example, the fraud scandal, you know,
네. 예를 들어, 사기 스캔들이라든지,
the kind of fraud that we're seeing play
우리가 벌어지는 걸 보고 있는 그런 종류의 사기가
out or, you know, any anything like that.
뭐 그런 어떤 것이든 말입니다.
And it's like, oh, OK, I need to
그러다 보면 '아, 좋습니다, 저는'
think and think about how to how to
어떻게, 어떻게 해야 할지 생각하고 또 생각해야 하고
have A.I. solve this. And I'm like,
AI로 이걸 풀게 하는 방법을 고민하게 됩니다.
oh, wait a minute. Why don't I ask
그런데 '아, 잠깐만, 왜 그냥 물어보지
the A.I.?
AI에게?'라고 생각하게 됩니다.
Yeah. Right. And then I go in there
네, 맞습니다. 그래서 들어가서
and I'm like, you know, how should I
'그러니까, 어떻게
do this?
하면 좋을까요?'라고 묻습니다.
And it's like, oh, well, here it's obvious
그리고 AI는 '아, 여기서는 명백하게
how you would do it.
이렇게 하면 됩니다'라고 하고요.
And here's, you know, the 18 steps that
그리고 '여기 18단계가 있고
you would take.
이 순서로 하시면 됩니다'라고 합니다.
And then I tell it, well, you know,
그리고 저는 '그러면, 그러니까,
OK, like, you know, interview me, you know,
좋습니다, 저를 인터뷰해 주세요,
interview me on all the open questions in
이 주제에서 아직 열린 질문들을 전부 가지고
the topic, you know, to get my thoughts
제 생각을 끌어내도록요,
on them.
그 질문들에 대해서입니다.
And then it starts, you know, it starts
그러면 AI가, 그러니까, 시작하고,
interrogating me. Right.
저를 캐묻기 시작합니다.
And then I'm like, OK, now give me
그리고 저는 '좋습니다, 이제
your point. And so it's just like, you
당신 관점을 주세요'라고 합니다. 그래서 이게 정말
know, as you know, like if you had
아시다시피, 예전에 일반 컴퓨터로
tried to do that with a normal computer
그걸 하려 했으면
in the old days, it just like stare
그냥 멀뚱히
at you.
쳐다보기만 했을 것입니다.
Right. So like this is really, really, really
맞습니다. 그러니까 이건 정말, 정말, 정말
different.
다릅니다.
And then, you know, I think the venture
그리고 저는 벤처 관점에서 보면
lens I would put on this is, you
이걸 이렇게 해석하게 되는데요,
know, in terms of the mechanics of venture
벤처 캐피털의 작동 메커니즘으로 말하면,
capital, you know, the sort of classic, you
그러니까 고전적인,
know, venture capital triangle is team, product and
벤처 캐피털의 고전적인 삼각형은 팀, 제품,
market.
그리고 시장입니다.
And you're always trying to kind of evaluate
그리고 항상 이 세 가지를
all three of those.
모두 평가하려고 합니다.
And people have always had, you know, different
또 사람들은 늘, 그러니까, 서로 다른
theories over the years of which of those
이론을 갖고 있었습니다, 그중 무엇이
are more important than the others and how
다른 것보다 더 중요한지, 그리고
they how they interact.
어떻게 상호작용하는지에 대해서입니다.
But the thing that basically every investor, public
하지만 기본적으로 거의 모든 투자자들이,
market investors, private investors, the thing that we're
공개시장 투자자든 사모 투자자든, 우리가
all trained to do is basically market sizing.
훈련받는 건 결국 시장 규모 산정입니다.
Like, you know, we're, you know, we're trained
그러니까, 우리는
to do technology analysis.
기술 분석을 하도록 훈련받고,
We're trained to do like, you know, background
배경
checks on people.
조사를 하도록 훈련받고,
And then we're trained to do market sizing.
그리고 시장 규모를 산정하도록 훈련받습니다.
Like, you know, OK, how big is this
예를 들어 '좋습니다, 이
market?
시장이 얼마나 크지?'라는 거죠.
Because, you know, the classic adage, right, is
왜냐하면 고전적인 격언이 있는데요,
if you if you put a huge amount
아주 큰 노력을
of effort into going after a small market,
작은 시장을 공략하는 데 쏟아부으면
you still get a small outcome.
결과도 결국 작다는 것입니다.
But there's a presumption in there, which is
그런데 거기에는 한 가지 전제가 있는데,
that you can actually predict market sizes on
그런 것들의 시장 규모를 실제로 예측할 수
these things.
있다는 전제입니다.
And the problem with that, again, is this
문제는, 다시 말하지만,
sort of this presumption that you can predict
오늘 존재하는 시장의 역학을 바탕으로
market sizes based on the dynamics that exist
시장 규모를 예측할 수 있다는
in the market today.
그 전제라는 것입니다.
But if there's a fundamental change on the
하지만 공급 측에 근본적인 변화가 있거나
supply side, if there's if there's a fundamental
근본적인
breakthrough, a fundamental capability that doesn't exist yet,
돌파구, 아직 존재하지 않는 근본 역량이 생기면,
you're not going to be able to accurately
시장 규모를 정확하게
model the market size because you can't you
모델링할 수가 없습니다. 왜냐하면
can't see it yet.
아직 그걸 볼 수 없기 때문입니다.
Like, you've changed one of the major variables
그러니까 큰 변수 하나가 바뀌었는데
and you can't do that.
그걸 기존 방식으로는 다룰 수가 없습니다.
And, you know, and then you could call
그리고 그걸
that the leap of faith or whatever.
믿음의 도약이라고 부르든 뭐라고 부르든,
But it's like, OK, if you if you
하지만 '좋습니다, 만약
make the change in the supply side, then
공급 측에 변화가 생기면
all of a sudden the market gets ten
시장이 갑자기 10배
or a hundred or a thousand times larger.
아니면 100배, 1000배로 커집니다.
Like, you can almost never validate that with
그걸 투자 시점에
math at the time of the investment.
수학으로 검증하는 건 거의 불가능합니다.
But that's the thing that makes the outperformers,
하지만 그게 바로 초과성과를 내는
you know, really go.
사람들을 만들어내는 요인입니다.
And I just I just think like as
그리고 저는 그냥, 그러니까
Ben and I kind of go through our
벤과 제가 경력을 쌓아가면서
careers, we just see more and more examples
점점 더 많은 사례를 보게 되는데요,
where the mistake that we or others make
우리나 다른 사람들이 저지르는 실수가
is, oh, this must be, you know, the
아, 그러니까 이건,
market for Uber and Lyft must be the
우버와 리프트의 시장은
market for taxi cabs.
택시 시장과 같아야 한다는 뜻입니다.
Right. Or, you know, the market. Yeah. Or
맞습니다. 그러니까 시장이요. 네. 또는
the market for cloud software must be the
클라우드 소프트웨어 시장도
same as the market for on prem software.
온프레미스 소프트웨어 시장과 같아야 한다는 식입니다.
Right.
그렇습니다.
Or the market for GPUs must be the
또는 GPU 시장은
market for people who like to play games.
게임을 좋아하는 사람들의 시장이라고 보는 것입니다.
Yes, exactly. And we just keep seeing example
네, 정확합니다. 그리고 저희는 계속해서 사례를
after example after example where the significant enough
사례 또 사례로 보는데, 충분히 큰
technology change, product change on the supply side
공급 측의 기술 변화, 제품 변화가
unlocks much larger markets.
훨씬 더 큰 시장을 열어젖힙니다.
And I think that's going to be I
그리고 저는 그것이 앞으로
mean, I think, frankly, that's going to be
그러니까, 솔직히 말씀드리면 그것이
like the single like dominant trend in investing
투자에서 단 하나의 지배적인 트렌드가
for like the next 30 years.
향후 30년 동안 이어질 것이라고 봅니다.
I think that's just going to like telescope
그건 그냥 망원경처럼
way out.
엄청나게 크게 확장될 겁니다.
The I think is so interesting, right, because
저는 그게 정말 흥미로운데요, 왜냐하면
from a technology perspective, it feels like you
기술 관점에서는 마치 여러분이
can build products pretty immediately that are going
바로 제품을 만들어서 곧
to win.
승리할 수 있을 것처럼 느껴지기 때문입니다.
And then A16Z starts to make a lot
그러면 a16z가 왜 그토록
more sense in that context where it's like
의미가 있는지도 그 맥락에서 더 이해가 되는데,
all of these other things.
이런 다른 모든 요소들이 있습니다.
It's how do you do go to market?
시장 진입은 어떻게 하십니까?
How do you do policy? Like, how do
정책은 어떻게 다루십니까? 그러니까 어떻게
you set the conditions for the actual best
진짜로 최고의
technology to win as quickly as possible?
기술이 가능한 빨리 이기도록 조건을 만드십니까?
Like, how do you think about all the
그러니까 그 모든
different things that you do there? And is
다양한 일들을 어떻게 생각하십니까? 그리고 그게
that the right way to think about it?
그렇게 접근하는 게 맞는 방식입니까?
Like the best technology should win and the
즉 최고의 기술이 이겨야 하고
platform is there to make sure that that
플랫폼은 그게
happens?
일어나게 보장하는 역할이라는 것입니까?
You know, the way we always thought about
저희가 항상 생각해 온 방식은
the firm was what can a partner do
이 회사에서 파트너가 무엇을 할 수 있느냐,
for an entrepreneur that will not only help
창업가를 위해 단지
them ensure their success,
성공을 보장하는 데 그치지 않고,
but help them kind of build the company
그들이 회사를
they want to build and the way they
원하는 모습으로, 원하는 방식으로
want to build it with the people they
그들이 함께하고 싶은 사람들과
want to build it with and the culture
함께 만들고, 그들이
that they are proud of.
자랑스러워할 문화를 세우도록 돕는 것이었습니다.
And to do that, there's many, many pieces.
그리고 그걸 하려면 정말 많은 요소가 필요합니다.
And a lot of it, you know, some
그리고 그중 상당 부분은, 즉, 일부는
of it is just like very fundamental.
아주 근본적인 것들입니다.
Like, can you do your business in the
예를 들면, 미국에서
United States of America? Can you do it
사업을 할 수 있습니까? 전 세계에서
in the world?
할 수 있습니까?
And so that's where the policy comes in.
그래서 거기에 정책이 들어옵니다.
It's just like a very basic question.
그냥 아주 기본적인 질문인 셈입니다.
And look, governments have a huge interest in
그리고 보시면, 요즘 정부는
technology these days, so like it's a necessary
기술에 엄청난 관심이 있어서, 이건 필수적인
one.
요소입니다.
A lot of the other things come down
다른 많은 것들은 결국
to, you know, how do you go from
그러니까 어떻게
being an inventor to being a competent CEO?
발명가에서 유능한 CEO로 넘어가느냐로 귀결됩니다.
And that really is a confidence game, for
그리고 그건 정말, 표현이 적절치 않다면 모르겠지만,
lack of a better word.
결국 자신감의 게임입니다.
And that, you know, it's very difficult to
그리고 뭘 하는지 모를 때
run an organization when you don't know what
조직을 운영하는 건 매우 어렵습니다,
you're doing, which nobody does when they're an
그리고 발명가라면 누구나
inventor.
처음에는 다 모를 수밖에 없습니다.
And you get tremendous amount of advice and
그런데 정말 엄청난 양의 조언을 받게 되는데,
advice that's often extremely bad and almost the
그 조언이 종종 극도로 나쁘고 거의
opposite of what you should be doing.
해야 할 일의 정반대인 경우도 많습니다.
And there are very few like the people
그리고 실제로 뭔가를 만들어 본 사람들은
who've actually built things don't have time to
시간이 거의 없어서
talk to.
대화하기가 어렵습니다.
They're often away building things. So you get
대부분은 또 무언가를 만들고 있습니다. 그래서
these like advisors and, you know, Silicon Valley
이런 조언자들, 그러니까 실리콘밸리의
people who tell you how to run your
회사 운영을 어떻게 하라고 말하는 사람들,
company, who to hire, this and that and
누구를 채용해야 하는지, 이것저것 다 말해 주는 사람들,
the other.
등등을 말하는 사람들이 있습니다.
And then those things turn out to be
그런데 나중에 보면 그런 것들이
wrong and you get to this confidence spiral.
틀린 것으로 드러나면서 자신감의 소용돌이에 빠지게 됩니다.
And so we, you know, the whole firm
그래서 저희는, 아시다시피, 회사 전체가
is built to put you in a kind
여러분을 일종의
of a virtuous confidence cycle as opposed to
악순환이 아니라 선순환의 자신감 사이클에
a vicious confidence cycle.
들어가게 하도록 설계되어 있습니다.
And that means like, oh, I need to
즉, 예를 들어 '제가
call somebody who's hard to get to like
연락하기 어려운 누군가에게,
an important CEO or like, you know, I've
예컨대 중요한 CEO에게 연락해야 한다'거나,
got to recruit a top end engineer or
'최고급 엔지니어를 영입해야 한다'거나,
I have to figure out how to market
'어떻게 마케팅을 해야 하는지 알아내야 한다'거나,
my product or I have to get to
'제 제품을 팔아야 한다'거나, 또는
somebody important in the government.
정부의 중요한 사람에게 접근해야 한다는 뜻입니다.
If I can do that, my confidence builds.
그걸 해내면 자신감이 올라갑니다.
If I can't do that, my confidence sinks.
못 해내면 자신감이 떨어집니다.
And so then, you know, once you're confident,
그리고 일단 자신감이 생기면,
you can make decisions faster.
결정을 더 빨리 내릴 수 있습니다.
You can, you know, build the company more
또 회사를 더 효과적으로 구축할 수 있고,
effectively. You can go for what you actually
실제로 여러분이 원하는 것을
want.
추구할 수 있습니다.
You can have confidence that, OK, what I
또 '좋아, 내가
want is the right thing as opposed to
원하는 것이 옳은 방향이다'라고 확신할 수 있는데,
what somebody is whispering in my ear, you
누군가가 제 귀에 속삭이는 말,
know, who is whatever, a CEO coach or
예컨대 CEO 코치든
a VC or this or that or the
VC든, 이것저것
other.
다른 누군가의 말과는 다릅니다.
And so the whole firm is designed to
그래서 회사 전체는 그렇게 하도록 설계되어 있습니다.
kind of enable that inventor to become a
그 발명가가 CEO가 되도록 돕고,
CEO and run their own company and put
자기 회사를 직접 운영하며,
their mark not just, you know, locally, but
그 흔적을 지역에만 남기는 것이 아니라,
in the world by being able to kind
전 세계에 남기도록,
of network to anyone.
누구와도 네트워킹할 수 있게 합니다.
And so that's that's a lot of what
그래서 그런 부분이
we're about.
저희가 하는 일의 큰 부분입니다.
Yeah.
네.
And I just add the sort of macro,
그리고 여기에 거시적인 관점을 하나 덧붙이면,
you know, kind of outside inlines on that
조금 바깥에서 보는 시각으로 말씀드리자면,
is it's just like, you know, we get
저희는 이런 분들과 함께 일할 기회를 얻는데,
to work with these, you know, super geniuses,
이분들은 정말 초천재들이십니다.
but they're specifically they are super geniuses at
다만 이분들은 특히
building products, building technologies.
제품을 만들고, 기술을 만들고 있습니다.
You know, to be a super genius at
아시다시피, 기술을 만드는 데 초천재가 되려면 말입니다.
building technologies generally requires you to have been
일반적으로 기술을 만드는 일은, 오랜 기간 몰입해 왔어야 합니다.
sitting in a lab or, you know, in
연구실에 앉아 있거나, 아시다시피,
front of a screen for, you know, 10
화면 앞에서, 아시다시피, 10년
or 20 years.
또는 20년을 보냈어야 합니다.
You know, these folks are fully capable of
아시다시피, 이런 분들은 충분히 해낼 수 있습니다.
understanding everything about the world at large.
세상 전반의 모든 것을 이해할 수 있다는 뜻입니다.
They just haven't done it yet.
다만 아직 그렇게 해 보지 않았을 뿐입니다.
They just haven't been out and they haven't
아직 밖으로 나가 보지도 않았고, 아직
met all the people and they haven't dealt
모든 사람들을 만나 보지도 않았으며, 아직
with all the issues in the real world.
현실 세계의 모든 문제를 겪어 보지도 않았습니다.
And so that leads to this kind of
그래서 그것이 이런 종류의 현상으로 이어집니다.
recurring, you know, kind of, I would say,
반복적으로 나타나는, 아시다시피, 제가 보기에는,
misimpression sometimes that people have.
사람들이 때때로 갖는 잘못된 인식입니다.
It's just like, well, if you build the
사람들은 결국 이렇게 말하기도 합니다.
right product, you know, if you build the
“올바른 제품만 만들면 된다”라고 말입니다.
breakthrough, whatever XYZ widget, like it's just the
“어떤 XYZ 위젯이든 혁신적인 돌파구만 만들면 된다”라고 말입니다.
world is obviously going to adopt it.
그러면 세상은 당연히 그것을 채택할 것이라는 것입니다.
Everybody's going to use it.
모두가 그것을 쓰게 될 것이라는 것입니다.
It's just obviously going to, you know, kind
당연히, 아시다시피, 모든 것이
of suit things.
잘 맞아떨어질 것이라는 것입니다.
And, you know, and basically if it doesn't,
그리고 아시다시피, 기본적으로 만약 그렇지 않다면,
the answer is the product is not good
답은 “제품이 충분히 좋지 않다”는 것입니다.
enough.
그저 “충분히 좋지 않다”는 것입니다.
And, you know, there's there's a little bit
그리고 아시다시피, 그 말에도 약간은
of truth to that.
진실이 있습니다.
Like, obviously, the better, the more breakthrough the
그러니까 당연히, 제품이 더 좋아질수록, 더 혁신적일수록
product, you know, the more there will just
아시다시피, 자연스럽게 더 많은
be organic traction.
유기적인 견인력이 생깁니다.
But what virtually everybody finds, you know, up
하지만 거의 모든 사람들이, 아시다시피, 결국 깨닫는 것은
to and including Elon Musk, right, what everybody
일론 머스크를 포함해서 모두가 깨닫는 것은,
finds is the real world is just like
현실 세계가 그냥
really, really big and really, really messy.
정말, 정말 크고 정말, 정말 복잡하고 혼란스럽다는 것입니다.
Right.
맞습니다.
And there are, you know, 8 billion people
그리고 아시다시피, 밖에는 80억 명의 사람들이
out there with like opinions that are not
여러분의 의견과는 반드시 같지 않은
necessarily, you know, your opinions.
각자의 의견을 가지고 있습니다.
And, you know, many of them have a
그리고 아시다시피, 그들 중 많은 이들은
real vote as to what is going to
무엇이 일어날지에 대해 실제로
happen with your product and with your company,
여러분의 제품과 회사에 어떤 일이 생길지에 대해,
you know, including whether anybody buys, you know,
아시다시피, 누군가가 여러분의 것을 사는지 여부까지 포함하여
your thing or, you know, all of the
여러분의 그것이라든지, 아시다시피, 각종
X factors that kick in, you know, all
작동하는 X 요인들, 아시다시피, 또
the different ways that, you know, people are
사람들이 아시다시피 여러 방식으로
going to come and try to, you know,
와서, 아시다시피,
cripple what you're doing or, you know, or
여러분이 하는 일을 망가뜨리려 하거나, 아시다시피, 혹은
maybe even worse than that, you know, just
어쩌면 그보다 더 나쁘게도, 아시다시피, 그냥
ignore you.
여러분을 무시해 버리기도 합니다.
Right.
맞습니다.
And so there is this there is this
그래서 이런, 이런 상황이 있습니다.
just there is this really big world out
그러니까 이런 정말 큰 세상이
there.
밖에 있다는 것입니다.
It's really complicated.
정말 복잡합니다.
It's really messy.
정말 혼란스럽습니다.
It's not necessarily in favor of new ideas.
새로운 아이디어에 반드시 호의적인 것은 아닙니다.
In many cases, it really, really doesn't like
많은 경우, 그것을 정말, 정말 싫어하며
them and wants to reject them.
그것을 거부하려고 합니다.
And there's real art and science, you know,
그리고 아시다시피, 여기에는 진짜 예술과 과학이 있습니다.
to Ben's point, to building the company around
벤의 말처럼, 요점은 회사가
the product and the founder to be able
제품과 창업자를 중심으로 만들어져야 한다는 것이며,
to take the breakthrough and be able to
그 돌파구를 잡아
take it successfully into the world.
그것을 성공적으로 세상으로 가져갈 수 있어야 한다는 것입니다.
And as far as we can tell, as
그리고 우리가 보기로는, 제가 보기로는,
far as I can tell, like that that
그, 그 과정이
process is getting, you know, hairier and more
아시다시피, 시간이 갈수록 더 험난해지고
complicated over time.
더 복잡해지고 있습니다.
Right.
맞습니다.
It's not getting easier.
더 쉬워지는 것이 아닙니다.
It seems like it's actually getting significantly harder.
실제로는 상당히 더 어려워지고 있는 것 같습니다.
And so, yeah, that's that's a big part
그래서, 맞습니다, 그것이 큰 부분이며
of what the what the firm is built
회사가 구축된 목적의 큰 부분은
to do is really help founders work through
창업자들이 그 과정을 정말로 헤쳐 나가도록
that.
돕는 것입니다.
And one of the things that Mark said
그리고 마크가 과거에 했던 말 중 하나가 있는데
in the past, which is really true, is
정말 맞는 말이었는데, 즉
like, look, as an inventor, you're looking for
“봐요, 발명가로서 여러분은
power, like a power boost.
힘, 말하자면 파워 부스트를 찾는 것입니다.”
So how do I go from little old
그렇다면 저는 어떻게 제 발명을 가진 보잘것없는 저에서
me with my invention to like I'm the
“나는 그 분야에서
important company in the space in the world?
세상에서 중요한 회사다”로 가느냐는 것입니다.
I can build momentum.
저는 추진력을 만들 수 있습니다.
I can get the best engineers.
저는 최고의 엔지니어들을 얻을 수 있습니다.
I can get the, you know, customers faster.
저는 아시다시피, 더 빠르게 고객을 확보할 수 있습니다.
And that that turns into a snowball and
그러면 그것이 눈덩이처럼 커지고
I'm rolling downhill.
저는 내리막으로 굴러가게 됩니다.
And so the whole firm is designed as
그래서 회사 전체는
like a very powerful entity that you can
여러분이 그냥 활용할 수 있는
just tap into and, you know, take our
아시다시피, 매우 강력한 실체로 설계되어 있습니다.
brand, take our connections, take our expertise and
우리 브랜드를 가져가고, 우리 연결망을 가져가고, 우리 전문성을 가져가서
become extremely powerful.
극도로 강력해지도록 만드는 것입니다.
Very fast.
아주 빠르게 말입니다.
Yeah.
맞습니다.
And by the way, this, this, this, you
그리고 참고로, 이, 이, 이게요,
know, this, this is the solution to the
아시다시피, 이것, 이것이 오랫동안 사람들이 우리에 대해 가졌던
puzzle that people have had about us for
퍼즐의 해답입니다. 즉, “와, 저 사람들은
a long time, which is, wow, it seems
오랫동안, 아시다시피,
like those guys are like, you know, awfully
너무 홍보를 많이 하는 것 같다”라는 것입니다.
promotional.
홍보성이 유난히 강해 보인다는 것입니다.
You know, they're, they're, you know, they're, you
아시다시피, 그들은, 그들은, 아시다시피, 그들은, 그러니까,
know, they do all this marketing stuff that,
이런 마케팅을 다 하고,
you know, they're doing all this politics stuff.
아시다시피, 이런 정치 활동도 다 하고 있다는 것입니다.
You know, they, they must be doing this
아시다시피, 그들이, 그들이 이것을
for ego reasons.
자기 과시를 위해 하는 것임에 틀림없다는 것입니다.
They must be really fool themselves.
스스로에게 취해 있는 것일 것이라는 것입니다.
You know, this must be about, you know,
아시다시피, 이것은, 그러니까,
They talk so much shit.
“저 사람들은 막말을 정말 많이 한다”라는 것입니다.
They talk so much shit, like the whole
“막말을 정말 많이 한다”는 이야기 전체가
thing.
전부라는 것입니다.
And at least, you know, for, and maybe,
그리고 적어도, 아시다시피, 그리고 어쩌면,
maybe, maybe, maybe it's possible, possible we talk
어쩌면, 어쩌면, 어쩌면 우리가 정말로
too much shit.
막말을 너무 많이 하고 있을 수도 있습니다.
I'll let other people judge that from time
그 평가는 다른 사람들이 때때로
to time, maybe.
하도록 두겠습니다, 어쩌면 말입니다.
However, however, from the beginning, the goal was
하지만, 하지만, 처음부터 목표는
to build the, the purpose of building the
지배적인 벤처 브랜드를 구축하는 것이었고, 그 목적은
dominant venture brand was precisely to be able
바로 결정적으로 필요한 시점에
to have the companies be able to borrow
회사들이 그것을 빌려 쓸 수 있게 하려는 것이었습니다.
that at the most critical points in their
그들의 성장에서 가장 중요한 시점들에서 말입니다.
development so that the companies can kind of
그래서 회사들이 일종의
use, use, use our force in the world
세상에서 우리 힘을, 힘을, 힘을
as a slingshot to basically build their own
새총처럼 사용하여 기본적으로 자기들만의
force.
힘을 만들 수 있게 하는 것입니다.
And, and I think that's worked really well.
그리고 저는 그것이 정말 잘 작동했다고 생각합니다.
And that's why we don't, you know, shrink
그래서 우리는 아시다시피, 이런 많은 것들에서
back from a lot of these things.
많이 물러서지 않는 것입니다.
Yeah.
맞습니다.
I wanted like, just squeeze something in and
저는 잠깐만 하나 끼워 넣고자 합니다.
then get right back on this conversation.
그리고 바로 이 대화로 돌아가겠습니다.
Talking too much shit is so interesting, but
막말을 너무 많이 한다는 얘기는 정말 흥미롭지만,
I really love it.
저는 그것을 정말 좋아합니다.
I think the thing that impressed me the
제가 가장 인상 깊었던 점은
most when I started working with the crypto
크립토 팀과 함께 일하기 시작했을 때
team was seeing never take the negative in
부정적인 말을 절대 개인적으로 받아들이지 않고
person and like never talk shit on a
어떤 기술에 대해서도 절대 험담하지 않으며
technology, never talk shit on a founder, never
어떤 창업자에 대해서도 절대 험담하지 않고, 절대
talk shit on a company.
어떤 회사에 대해서도 험담하지 않는다는 점이었습니다.
Like, how do you even train for that?
그런 것을 대체 어떻게 훈련하십니까?
Cause that really, really impressed me.
그게 정말, 정말 인상 깊었습니다.
Well, we train for that.
저희는 그것을 훈련합니다.
So, uh, we have a culture, um, that
그래서, 음, 저희에게는 문화가 있습니다.
is written culture that you cannot join the
그것은 문서로 정리된 문화이며, 그 문서에 서명하지 않으면
firm unless you sign a document, uh, the
문서에 서명하지 않으면 회사에 합류할 수 없습니다.
culture document and says you will adhere to
그 문화 문서에 서명해서
this culture.
이 문화를 준수하겠다고 해야 합니다.
And, uh, then you must sit through one
그리고 또, 저와 함께
hour with me, uh, understanding the culture and
한 시간 동안 문화를 이해하는 시간을 반드시 가져야 하고,
fundamentally on that, you know, our whole point
그리고 근본적으로는, 아시다시피, 저희의 핵심은
is if you want to do something larger
자기 자신보다 더 큰 일을 하고
than yourself and make the world a better
세상을 더 나은 곳으로 만들고자 한다면,
place, we are a hundred percent for it.
저희는 100% 그 편이라는 것입니다.
And we do not care.
그리고 저희는 상관하지 않습니다.
Uh, you know, like if in the moment
그러니까, 예를 들어 그 순간에
we think you're making a mistake or like
저희가 당신이 실수하고 있다고 생각하든
the ideas and good, and it doesn't matter
아이디어가 좋지 않다고 보더라도, 그게 중요하지는 않고
if we invest in you or don't invest
저희가 당신에게 투자하든 하지 않든
in you.
상관없습니다.
Um, we're for that.
그러니까, 저희는 그런 일을 지지합니다.
We are dream builders.
저희는 꿈을 만드는 사람들입니다.
We're not dream killers.
꿈을 짓밟는 사람들이 아닙니다.
We're not here to be like the analytical
저희는 분석적으로
smarty pants who makes ourselves look smart by
자기만 똑똑해 보이려고
making somebody else look stupid.
남을 바보로 만드는 잘난 체를 하러 온 게 아닙니다.
And that's just, that's fundamental to how we
그리고 그게 바로, 그게 저희가
think about the world.
세상을 바라보는 방식의 근본입니다.
Um, so like anybody who's trying to push
그러니까, 세상을 앞으로 나아가게 하고
the world forward and make it better, like
더 나아지게 하려는 사람이라면 누구든,
whether we agree with their method or not,
저희가 그들의 방식에 동의하든 아니든,
like we're for it.
저희는 그들을 지지합니다.
And so, uh, you, we just ask you
그래서, 그러니까, 저희는 당신에게
to sign up to that idea before you
합류하기 전에 그 생각에 동의해 달라고
ever join.
요청하는 것뿐입니다.
Catherine said that, that, uh, you know, we
캐서린이, 그러니까, '우리는
believe in the future and bet the firm
미래를 믿고 회사 전체를
that way was, should actually be the number
그 방향에 걸어야 한다'는 게 사실상
one, uh, kind of value in the, in
문화에서 1순위 가치가 되어야 한다고
the culture.
말했습니다.
By the way, that, that, that was Mark's.
참고로, 그건 마크의 아이디어였습니다.
Um, you know, I, I did the wording,
그러니까, 제가 문구를 다듬긴 했지만,
so I give myself a little credit, but
그래서 제게도 약간의 공은 주고 싶지만,
that was Mark's idea.
아이디어는 마크의 것이었습니다.
Do you think that should be number one?
그게 1순위가 되어야 한다고 생각하십니까?
Do you think that is number one in,
실제로도 그게 1순위라고
in practice?
보십니까?
Do you think first class business in a
‘최고 수준의 방식으로 최고 수준의 비즈니스를 한다’는 게
first class way is like, if you were
만약 오늘 그 문서를 다시 쓴다면,
to rewrite the doc today, what is the
회사에서 가장 중요한 것이
most important thing in the, in the firm?
무엇인지와 같은 것이라고 보십니까?
Well, look, I mean, the culture document is
음, 보십시오, 문화 문서는
seven things that, um, you know, and the
일곱 가지 항목으로 되어 있는데요, 그리고
culture is more than that.
문화는 그보다 훨씬 더 많습니다.
Every culture is more than seven, seven ideas
어떤 문화든 일곱 가지 아이디어로만
and kind of seven sets of behaviors.
또는 일곱 가지 행동 양식으로만 설명되지는 않습니다.
But those are the ones that all seven
하지만 그 일곱 가지는
of them that we really expect everybody to
저희가 모든 구성원이
live to.
정말로 실천하길 기대하는 것들입니다.
Um, so I, I don't know if I
그래서, 제가 그걸
rank them in that sense because they all
그런 의미에서 순위를 매길 수 있을지는 모르겠습니다, 모두가
go together.
서로 맞물려 있기 때문입니다.
They're part of a single thing.
그것들은 하나의 동일한 체계의 일부입니다.
So, um, you know, we believe in the
그러니까, 음, 아시다시피 저희는
future means that we believe in the people
미래를 믿는다는 건 미래를 만드는 사람들을 믿는다는 뜻이고
who build the future, which means we're not
미래를 만드는 분들을 믿는다는 건, 저희가
going to criticize them, which means, you know,
그분들을 비난하지 않겠다는 뜻이며, 아시다시피,
we're not going to, we're not going to
저희는, 저희는
be on the attack side of that.
그 일에서 공격하는 편에 서지 않겠다는 것입니다.
We're never going to attack the future. We're
저희는 결코 미래를 공격하지 않을 것이며,
going to try and make, you know, there
그러니까, 미래를 만들려고 노력할 것입니다.
are going to be problems with how we
미래를 만드는 과정에는 문제가 생길 수도 있지만
build the future, but we're going to try
저희는 그래도 노력해서
and make it the best future we can.
가능한 한 최고의 미래를 만들겠습니다.
We're not going to try and live in
그리고 저희는
the past.
과거에 살려고 하지 않을 것입니다.
Uh, and so that you can't do that.
음, 그래서 그렇게는 할 수 없습니다.
If you're attacking entrepreneurs all the time, you
기업가들을 늘 공격하고 있으면
can't do that.
그렇게 할 수 없습니다.
If you show up, you know, an hour
또 누군가 회사를 만들려는데, 아시다시피,
late to meet with somebody who's trying to
만나기로 하고 한 시간이나 늦게 나타나면
build a company, you can't do those kinds
그런 종류의 행동은
of things.
할 수 없습니다.
And so every part of the culture, I
그래서 문화의 모든 부분은, 제 생각에는,
think, is in support of, we want to
결국 저희가
build a better future. Like that is, that's
더 나은 미래를 만들고 싶다는 것을 뒷받침합니다.
why we're here.
그게 우리가 여기 있는 이유입니다.
Haber, uh, in his piece, firm kind of
하버가, 음, 자신의 글에서 'Firm > Fund'라고 하며
greater than fund talks about, you know, a
펀드보다 펌이 더 크다는 관점에서 말하듯이,
firm is something that tries to build a
펌이란 시간이 지날수록
compounding competitive advantage.
복리로 쌓이는 경쟁우위를 구축하려는 존재입니다.
And he points to one thing for Apollo,
그리고 그는 아폴로에 대해 한 가지를 지적하고,
one thing for Goldman. If you had to
골드만에 대해서도 한 가지를 지적합니다.
pick a thing, what are you compounding?
만약 한 가지를 고른다면, 무엇을 복리로 쌓고 계신가요?
Like, what is the competitive advantage that you're,
즉, 시간이 지나며 구축하고 있는 경쟁우위가
that you're building over time? Do you think
무엇이라고 보십니까, 여기서는요?
here?
어떻게 생각하십니까?
Reputation.
평판입니다.
We, Mark and I talked about that from
저희는, 마크와 저는
the day we started the firm.
회사를 시작한 날부터 그 이야기를 해왔습니다.
And, and by, by the way, there were
그리고 참고로,
times when it was like, well, we're investing
가끔은 '우리가
an awful lot in reputation.
평판에 너무 많이 투자하는 것 아닌가' 싶은 때도 있었습니다.
Um, and you know, it's taken a while.
음, 그리고 아시다시피 시간이 좀 걸렸습니다.
Uh, but it is, that's what we compete
하지만 그게 바로 우리가 경쟁하는 지점입니다.
on.
그것으로 승부합니다.
Like when we, when we talk to an
예를 들어 우리가 어떤
entrepreneur, um, and they're comparing us to another
기업가와 이야기할 때, 음, 그분이 우리를 다른
firm, we say, find an entrepreneur that's taken
펌과 비교한다면, 두 곳 모두에서 투자를 받은 기업가를 찾아보라고 합니다.
investment from both firms, see what they say.
그리고 그 사람이 뭐라고 하는지 들어보라고 하죠.
Like that's our answer to everything.
그게 모든 질문에 대한 우리의 답입니다.
Uh, we, we build reputation.
음, 우리는 평판을 쌓습니다.
Every relationship matters.
모든 관계가 중요합니다.
Everybody who we touch, we try and touch
우리가 접점이 생기는 모든 사람과
as many people as we can.
가능한 한 많은 관계를 맺으려고 합니다.
And we try and, um, represent in the
그리고 우리는, 음, 가능한 한
very, very best way possible to build reputation
최선의 방식으로 행동해 시간이 지나며 평판을 쌓으려고 합니다.
over time.
시간을 두고요.
And that compounds and compounds and compounds across,
그리고 그것은 계속 복리로 쌓이고 쌓이고 쌓여서,
uh, entrepreneurs, across industries, across sectors, across, you
음, 기업가들 사이에서, 산업 전반에서, 섹터 전반에서, 그러니까
know, everybody from, you know, people in the
정부에 있는 사람들부터
government to, uh, you know, people in, uh,
또, 음, 그러니까,
in companies that, that we don't invest in.
우리가 투자하지 않는 회사에 있는 사람들까지요.
And, um, anybody who is anywhere in the
그리고, 음, 기술 업계 어디에 있든 누구든지
world of technology, we want, we want them
우리는 그들이 우리를 알기를 원하고,
to know us and we want them to,
그리고 우리를
uh, think of us as the best, uh,
음, 비즈니스를 함께하기에 가장 좋은, 음,
firm to do business with.
파트너 펌이라고 생각해 주기를 바랍니다.
Yeah.
네.
And then that, and then that transfers, of
그리고 그게, 그리고 물론 그게
course, that transfers from us, that transfers to
우리에게서 포트폴리오 회사들로
the portfolio companies, right?
전이됩니다, 그렇죠?
So that, which is the goal of it,
그게 목표입니다.
which is that then as a consequence, when
그래서 그 결과로,
a, when a company takes investment from us,
어떤 회사가 우리로부터 투자를 받으면
now they, they're basically able to use our
그들은 기본적으로 우리의
reputation to get themselves through the, through those,
평판을 활용해서 그들 스스로
those, those, those, you know, kind of key
그런, 그런, 그러니까 핵심적인
growth phases with, you know, with, with potential
성장 단계에서, 그러니까 잠재적인
customers and with recruits and with downstream investors
고객들, 채용 후보자들, 그리고 이후 단계 투자자들과도요.
and with, you know, regulators and with, you
그리고, 그러니까, 규제 당국과도, 그리고
know, all, all these different, you know, forces
이런저런 서로 다른 힘들과도,
in the external society.
외부 사회에서 말입니다.
Um, so the, the, the, the, the reputation
음, 그래서 그, 그, 그, 그, 그 평판은
pays off, not just for us, but it
우리에게만이 아니라,
pays off in the form of, uh, what
포트폴리오 기업들이
our, what our portfolio companies are able to
그 결과로 할 수 있게 되는 것의
do as a result.
형태로도 보상이 돌아옵니다.
So having done this for 16, 17 years,
그래서 16~17년 동안 이 일을 해오시면서,
like, are there things about building and transferring
평판을 구축하고 이전하는 것에 대해
reputation that you've learned that are not obvious?
겉으로는 잘 보이지 않는 배운 점들이 있습니까?
Because to me, like, it would almost seem
왜냐하면 제게는, 그러니까, 거의
that it's a battery.
그게 배터리처럼 보입니다.
And if you give it to one company
그리고 그것을 한 회사에 주었는데
that messes it up, then the whole thing
그 회사가 망치면, 그러면 전체가
kind of falls apart.
어느 정도 무너지는 것 같습니다.
But actually it, maybe it's like love to
그런데 사실은, 어쩌면 사랑 같아서
be like super cheap, like it just grows
너무 진부한 비유를 쓰자면, 줄수록 더 커지는 것 같습니다.
the more you give it.
더 많이 줄수록 그렇습니다.
Are there other things like that, that, that
그런 것 말고도, 또 다른 것들이, 그러니까,
you've learned?
배우신 것이 있습니까?
Well, look, I, I, I do think that
음, 글쎄요, 저는, 저는, 저는
that's a correct insight in that, you know,
그게 맞는 통찰이라고 생각합니다, 그러니까,
one mistake is much more powerful than, you
한 번의 실수가 훨씬 더 강력하다는 점에서요.
know, one good deed.
아시다시피, 한 번의 선행보다요.
Um, so, you know, one person being obnoxious,
음, 그래서, 그러니까, 누군가가 무례하게 굴거나,
uh, who's in the firm or lying to
그 사람이 회사 안에 있든, 창업자에게 거짓말을 하든
an entrepreneur or doing something like that is
그런 일을 하는 것은
causes much more damage than you can do
제대로 했을 때보다 훨씬 더 큰 피해를
by doing that correctly.
초래합니다.
Uh, you know, five or 10 times, um,
반대로 그 일을 제대로 하는 것은
which is why you have to be so
다섯 번, 열 번 하더라도요.
vigilant about it.
그래서 그 부분에 대해 그렇게
Like you, you, you can't, you cannot tolerate
경계를 늦추지 말아야 합니다.
that kind of behavior.
그런 행동은 용납할 수 없습니다.
Um, but I, I, I think that the,
음, 하지만 저는, 저는, 저는 그,
the thing, the biggest thing that I've learned
제가 배운 것 중 가장 큰 것은
is it takes a long time to build
평판을 쌓는 데 시간이 오래 걸린다는 것입니다.
a reputation.
평판을 말입니다.
Uh, and, but once you do, it's, it's,
음, 그런데 한 번 쌓고 나면, 그게, 그게,
it's the most powerful thing.
가장 강력한 것이 됩니다.
It really does compound.
정말로 복리처럼 불어납니다.
Um, and just to give you an example,
음, 예를 하나 들어드리면,
look, when Mark and I raised fund one,
보세요, 마크와 제가 1호 펀드를 모금했을 때,
it was a $300 million fund.
그건 3억 달러 펀드였습니다.
Um, I think it took about six months
음, 모금하는 데 약 6개월 걸렸던 것 같습니다.
to raise.
모금하는 데요.
Uh, we had a lot of meetings.
미팅을 정말 많이 했습니다.
I can't, I can't count how many meetings.
미팅이 몇 번이었는지 셀 수도 없습니다.
Um, some people did not treat us very
음, 어떤 사람들은 저희를 매우
well as, uh, Trump might say, they didn't
좋게 대하지 않았습니다. 그러니까, 트럼프가 말하듯이, 그들은
treat me well at all.
저를 전혀 좋게 대하지 않았습니다.
Uh, very badly.
아주 나쁘게 말입니다.
Um, and you know, this raise, which was
음, 그런데 이번 모금은, 그러니까,
$15 billion when we actually raised the fund,
실제로 펀드를 모금했을 때 150억 달러였는데,
I think Mark did one AMA and I
마크가 AMA를 한 번 했고 저는
did one AMA.
AMA를 한 번 했습니다.
And I don't, I don't know that I
그리고 저는, 저는 이것과 관련해서
took another meeting on this fundraise.
추가로 미팅을 하나 더 했는지도 모르겠습니다.
Uh, and it was done on the, on
음, 그리고 그건, 그, 그
the reputation.
평판에 기반해서 이루어졌습니다.
And so, um, that's a, that's a heck
그래서, 음, 그건 정말
of a change, you know, and look, a
엄청난 변화입니다, 아시다시피. 그리고 보세요,
lot of, not that we don't, we talk
물론 투자자들과 대화하지 않는 게 아니고,
to our investors all the time.
항상 투자자들과 대화합니다.
I mean, I've been all around the world,
그러니까, 저는 전 세계를 돌아다니며
uh, building relationships and so forth, but when
관계를 구축하는 등 여러 일을 해왔습니다만, 우리가
we came to ask for money, uh, it
우리가 돈을 요청하러 갔을 때는, 그러니까, 그것은
was raised entirely on the reputation.
전적으로 평판만으로 모은 것이었습니다.
I think, Paki, I think the, um, the
패키, 제 생각에는, 음, 그
external environment has changed, you know, enormously.
외부 환경이, 아시다시피, 엄청나게 바뀌었습니다.
Um, and so, you know, we've, we've lived
어, 그래서 아시다시피 저희는, 저희는
this, you know, as you have and many
이걸 겪어왔고, 당신도 그렇고 많은
others, we've, you know, this incredible transformation where
다른 분들도 그렇듯이, 이런 엄청난 변화가 있었는데
tech both is like much, much, much larger
기술이 훨씬, 훨씬, 훨씬 더 커졌고
and more central now than it was in
지금은 그때보다 훨씬 더 중심이 되었습니다,
2009 when we started.
저희가 시작한 2009년과 비교하면 말입니다.
But also, you know, the, the level of,
하지만 또 한편으로는, 아시다시피 그 수준이,
let's just say engagement on the, on the
이를테면 참여도라고 할까요, 그
part of the world attack is, you know,
전 세계가 기술에 대해 보이는 반응이, 아시다시피,
the, the level of intensity on everything from,
모든 면에서의 강도 수준이,
you know, you know, attacks, you know, criticism,
공격이라든지, 비판이라든지,
you know, by the way, you know, completely
아시다시피, 그런데 또 완전히
justifiable questions, you know, impact on society.
정당한 질문들, 사회에 미치는 영향 같은 것들이요.
You know, the, the, the intensity level is,
아시다시피 그 강도 수준이,
you know, I don't know, it's like a,
글쎄요, 마치
I don't know, like a thousand X of
한 천 배쯤은
what it was 16 years ago.
16년 전과는 다른 것 같습니다.
And so I, I think, you know, I
그래서 저는, 아시다시피,
think to your question, I think we've, we've
질문하신 것에 대해 말씀드리면, 저희는
really tried to kind of rise to that,
그에 걸맞게 대응하려고 정말 노력해 왔고,
uh, on both sides.
양쪽 모두에서입니다.
Like we're really trying to help these, you
즉 저희는 이, 아시다시피 이런 회사들이
know, these companies get to levels of scale
규모를
that nobody ever thought was possible before.
예전에 누구도 가능하다고 생각하지 못했던 수준까지 키우도록 돕고 있습니다.
But at the same time, we're trying to
하지만 동시에 저희는
help them deal with pressures that previous generations
이전 세대의
of founders, you know, generally didn't have to
창업자들은 대체로 겪지 않아도 됐던 압박을
deal with.
잘 견딜 수 있도록 돕고 있습니다.
Yeah.
네.
You seem like you uniquely maybe of anybody
당신은 제가 아는 사람들 중에서도 아마 유독
that I know have fun taking, you know,
이런, 아시다시피,
like engaging in these conversations.
이런 대화에 참여하는 것을 즐기는 것처럼 보입니다.
And I wrote about it a little bit
저도 그 글에서 그 이야기를 조금 썼습니다.
in the piece, but like kind of stepping
그 글에서 말입니다, 하지만 조금 한 발 물러서서 생각해 보겠습니다.
outside the situation and viewing it.
그 상황 밖으로 나와서 바라보는 것입니다.
I don't like what goes on in your
그런 상황에서 머릿속에서 어떤 일이 벌어지는지
head in these situations.
저는 잘 모르겠습니다.
Like, are you having as much fun as
그러니까, 겉으로 보이는 만큼 정말 즐거우십니까?
it looks like?
겉으로 보기에는 그렇게 보입니다.
Does it take a toll ever kind of
또 그렇게 '화살을 맞는' 일이 부담이 되기도 합니까?
like taking the arrows?
그런 공격을 감수할 때 말입니다.
What does it feel like in these?
그럴 때는 어떤 기분입니까?
Yeah.
네.
Ben, what?
벤, 어떻습니까?
Why don't you, yeah.
네, 말씀해 주시겠습니까?
Ben will give the rational response.
벤이 이성적인 답변을 해줄 것입니다.
Yeah.
네.
I would say it's.
제 생각에는 그렇습니다.
I'll give the vote.
제가 한 표를 던지겠습니다.
I mean, it gets emotional from time to
그러니까, 가끔은 감정적으로 되기도 합니다.
time.
때때로 말입니다.
Right.
그렇습니다.
Because.
왜냐하면 말입니다.
You know what goes into building these things
이런 것들을 만드는 데 무엇이 들어가는지도 알고,
and, you know, the intentions of the people
그것을 만드는 사람들의 의도도 알고 있으며,
building them and, you know, like the kind
그들이 세상에 미치는 영향도 알고
of impact they have on the world.
있기 때문입니다.
And then to just get like, you know,
그런데도 그냥, 아시다시피, 공격을 받게 됩니다.
and a lot of the attacks tend to
그리고 공격의 많은 부분이
be in the form of character assassinations and
인신공격 형태로
so forth.
나오곤 합니다.
And now everybody thinks Mark's Jewish, you know,
그리고 이제는 모두가 마크가 유대인이라고 생각하는데,
just so they can attack him more.
그를 더 공격하기 위해서입니다.
It turns out people love to attack Jewish
알고 보니 사람들은 유대인을 공격하는 것을
people.
좋아하더군요.
So I welcome him into that.
그래서 저는 그를 그 대열로 환영합니다.
My new name.
제 새 이름입니다.
Packy is in certain political circles is Andy.
패키는 어떤 정치권에서는 앤디로 불립니다.
Uh, as, as, uh, as, um, Andy Horowitz.
즉 앤디 호로위츠로 말입니다.
Because people think that people think Andrew and
왜냐하면 사람들은 앤드루를, 그리고
the, and the, and the swamp fringes of
인터넷의 이른바 늪지대 변두리에서는
the internet.
말입니다.
People think Andrew Horowitz is a Jewish person.
사람들은 앤드루 호로위츠가 유대인이라고 생각합니다.
Yeah.
네.
Um, and so I, I now introduce myself
그래서 이제 저는 제 소개를
as.
이렇게 합니다.
Yeah.
네.
I didn't have that in my Twitter bio.
저는 트위터 프로필에 그걸 적어 두지 않았습니다.
I did have it in my Twitter bio.
저는 트위터 프로필에 그걸 적어 두었습니다.
My real name is Andy.
제 진짜 이름은 앤디입니다.
It's Andy Horowitz, but, uh, and I am
제 이름은 앤디 호로위츠입니다.
Jewish, but I took it down.
그리고 저는 유대인이지만, 그걸 내렸습니다.
Yeah.
네.
But I, I would say mostly it, it's
하지만 제 생각에 대체로는 그렇습니다.
just like, it's an amazing, um,
그냥 정말 놀라운 일입니다.
it's just like an amazing thing and amazing
정말 놀라운 일이자 놀라운
privilege, uh, to kind of be in the
그 한가운데에 있게 된 것은 일종의 특권입니다.
center of it all.
모든 것의 중심에 있다는 뜻입니다.
Uh, and, you know, like, and then the
그리고 그러면서도 그에 따르는
responsibility that goes with it, that you, you
책임이 있는데, 그러니까, 그러니까,
have to kind of try and help drive
세상이 올바른 답으로 가도록
the world to the right answer.
어느 정도는 도와서 이끌어야 합니다.
Uh, but like, it's, I don't know if
하지만, 그러니까, 저는 그게,
fun is the right word, but like, it's
재미라는 말이 맞는지는 모르겠지만,
special.
특별합니다.
It's like, we've gotten to a very special
우리는 매우 특별한
position and I think, you know, both of
위치에 이르렀고, 그리고 제 생각에
us try and take it as seriously as
우리 둘 다 가능한 한 진지하게
we can.
그것을 받아들이려고 합니다.
And, you know, like things happen and we
그리고 여러 일이 생기면 우리는
have very, very long discussions about how we
어떤 일에 어떻게 대응해야 하는지에 대해
should react to certain things.
아주, 아주 긴 논의를 합니다.
Um, how we should not react to certain
또 어떤 일에는 어떻게 대응하지 말아야 하는지,
things, um, what we can take a position
어떤 것에 대해 입장을 취할 수 있고
on, what we shouldn't take a position on.
어떤 것에는 입장을 취하지 말아야 하는지도 논의합니다.
Um, uh, and, you know, just to have,
그리고, 그러니까, 그냥,
just to be, you know, at this stage
그러니까, 인생의 이 단계에서
of life, to be able to be talking
그런 이야기를 할 수 있다는 것이,
about that as opposed to, um, the things
우리가
that we had to talk about when we
Netscape나, 또는, 또는, Opsware를 만들 때
were building Netscape or, or, or Opsware.
이야기해야 했던 것들과는 다르다는 점입니다.
Like it's, it's amazing.
정말 놀랍습니다.
Uh, and, uh, you know, I, I definitely
그리고 저는 분명히
wouldn't trade it.
이것과 바꾸고 싶지 않습니다.
Um, and, and look, we're, we've been through,
그리고 보십시오, 우리는 겪어 왔고,
we've been criticized so much at this point
지금까지 너무 많은 비판을 받아 와서,
that like it really, it bothers interestingly, which
흥미롭게도, 이제는 그게 정말로 신경 쓰이는데,
I never thought I'd see is it kind
제가 볼 줄은 몰랐던 점은 그것이
of bothers people inside the firm much more
회사 내부 사람들을 훨씬 더 신경 쓰이게 한다는 것이고,
than it bothers Mark or me.
마크나 저보다 더 그렇다는 점입니다.
Sure.
그렇습니다.
And I am just for the record studying
그리고 참고로 말씀드리면 저는
for my bar mitzvah.
제 바르 미츠바를 준비하고 있습니다.
Yeah.
네.
The half Torah.
하프타라입니다.
You, you need to learn your, your half
당신은, 당신은 하프타라
Torah tropes.
트로프(선율)를 배워야 합니다.
Yeah.
네.
How do you avoid at this point becoming
그렇다면 지금 시점에서 어떻게
a big company?
대기업이 되는 것을 피하십니까?
Like this is becoming a big organization.
이제 큰 조직이 되어 가고 있는데,
How do you avoid being a big company?
어떻게 대기업이 되는 것을 피하십니까?
Google wanted to avoid that.
Google도 그걸 피하고 싶어 했고,
Like everyone wants to avoid that.
모두가 그걸 피하고 싶어 합니다.
How do you actually do that?
실제로 어떻게 그렇게 하십니까?
Yeah.
네.
So I think a lot of that is
그래서 그 상당 부분은
organizational design.
조직 설계라고 생각합니다.
I mean, it, so if you look at
그러니까, 만약
the companies that didn't feel like big companies,
오랫동안 대기업처럼 느껴지지 않았던 회사들을 보면,
companies for a long time, they, they had
그들은 오랜 기간 동안
very, very, very thoughtful design to the organization.
조직을 매우, 매우, 매우 신중하게 설계했습니다.
And if you look at the firm, um,
그리고 우리 조직을 보면, 음,
you know, the crypto group or the infra
예를 들어 크립토 그룹이나 인프라
group or the, um, you know, the apps
그룹, 혹은 앱
group or the American dynamism group, they, they
그룹이나 아메리칸 다이내미즘 그룹이 있는데, 그들은
all feel like small companies.
모두 작은 회사처럼 느껴집니다.
And they're, they're, they're small companies with a
그리고 그들은
kind of very specific kind of support.
매우 구체적인 지원을 받는 작은 회사들입니다.
Uh, you know, in terms of the brand,
예를 들어 브랜드 측면에서,
in terms of, uh, fundraising and other kinds
펀드레이징과 다른 종류의
of things.
일들 측면에서 말입니다.
Um, but he, you know, the, the, the
음, 하지만
fundraising team is a small group.
펀드레이징 팀은 작은 그룹입니다.
And so the every, and every group is
그래서 각 그룹은
very autonomous from every other group.
다른 모든 그룹으로부터 매우 자율적입니다.
Like, uh, there's integration points, but they're, they're
통합 지점이 있기는 하지만, 그것들은
very simple.
매우 단순합니다.
And so, you know, for the most part,
그래서요, 대체로는요,
there, there's some that are more complicated than
그중에는 다른 것들보다 더 복잡한 것들도 있고요,
others.
그렇지 않은 것도 있습니다.
Um, and so, you know, that's what makes
음, 그래서요, 그런 점이
it, you know, the, the beauty of a,
그러니까요, 어떤, 어떤 매력을 만들고요,
of a small place is you can just
작은 조직의 장점은 그냥
sketch it done.
대략 구상만 하고 끝낼 수 있다는 점입니다.
The beauty of a big place is you're
큰 조직의 장점은
very powerful.
아주 강력하다는 점입니다.
Um, and so we try and kind of
음, 그래서 저희는
blend those two.
그 두 가지를 어느 정도 섞으려고 합니다.
We took a lot.
저희는 많은 것을 참고했습니다.
We, Mark and I borrowed a lot.
저와 마크는 많은 것을 차용했습니다.
Um, early on, we really studied Hewlett Packard,
음, 초기에 저희는 휴렛팩커드를 정말 많이 연구했는데요,
uh, which the, the original Hewlett Packard before
그러니까 컴퓨터 사업이
the computer business kind of swallowed the company
회사를 사실상 삼켜버리기 전의
was very much like this.
원래 휴렛팩커드가 바로 이런 모습이었습니다.
They had, uh, they were like a series
그들은, 음, 마치 일련의
of companies inside a company and, and that's
회사 안의 회사들로 구성된 것 같았고, 그리고
a lot how we are.
저희도 상당 부분 그렇게 운영합니다.
How do you vet GPs or like, it
GP(제너럴 파트너)는 어떻게 검증하시나요, 그러니까
seems like you have to put a lot
각 팀을 운영하는 사람들에게
of trust in the people that are running
상당한 신뢰를 둬야 하는 것처럼 보이는데요,
the different teams.
각기 다른 팀을 운영하니까요.
If the whole thing is reputation, but you
전체가 평판이 핵심이라면, 그런데
need to be able to scale by having
이런 분산된 팀들로 확장도
these kinds of decentralized teams.
할 수 있어야 하잖습니까.
Is there anything that you do there that's,
그 과정에서 하시는 것 중에,
that's unique or, or weird, uh, that ensures
특이하다거나, 혹은 좀 독특하다거나 한데, 음, 해서
that kind of like no one group can
어떤 한 그룹도
infect the whole?
전체를 망치지 못하게 하는 것이 있나요?
Well, I think, look, first of all, in
음, 제 생각엔요, 우선 첫째로,
order to lead one of those groups, you
그런 그룹 중 하나를 이끌려면
just have to have been here and performed
여기서 오랫동안 일하며 성과를
for a long time.
꾸준히 내왔어야 합니다.
So that, that, that's kind of the first
그래서 그게, 그게 일종의 첫 번째
thing.
조건입니다.
So we just know you extremely well.
그래서 저희는 여러분을 아주 잘 압니다.
We're not, we're not interviewing people for that
그런 자리를 위해 외부에서 사람을
job from the outside.
면접으로 뽑지는 않습니다.
Like you can't get that job from the
그러니까 그 자리는 외부에서
outside.
얻을 수 없습니다.
And then, you know, I would say because
그리고 또, 아시다시피, 제 말은, 왜냐하면
our culture is so different than other venture
저희 문화가 다른 벤처
firms, you know, for, for better or worse,
펌들과는 너무 다르기 때문인데요, 좋든 나쁘든요,
we're just different that we don't hire a
저희는 그냥 달라서 이제는
lot of outside GPs anymore.
외부 GP를 많이 채용하지 않습니다.
We generally try to hire people at an
대체로는 커리어의 더
earlier stage of their career and kind of
초기 단계에서 사람을 채용해서
grow them into what we do.
저희 방식으로 성장시키려고 합니다.
Um, and that's where much, much better for
음, 그리고 그게 저희에게는 훨씬, 훨씬
us.
더 잘 맞습니다.
I would say in general, although we have
대체로는 그렇다고 말씀드리겠지만, 다만 저희도
like, uh, all of us came from the
음, 원래 멤버들은 모두 어느 시점에는
outside at one point of the original cast.
외부에서 들어왔던 사람들이기도 합니다.
That makes sense.
이해가 됩니다.
Um, kind of winding down here, but Mark,
음, 이제 마무리로 넘어가 보겠습니다만, 마크,
you said that, uh, I think you got
아까 말씀하시길, 음, 한때
shit at one point for saying the VC
벤처캐피털(VC)이
was going to be the last job, uh,
세상에서 마지막 직업이 될 거라고 말했다가, 음,
in, in the world.
상당히 비난을 받으셨다고 하셨죠.
Uh, you know, if you, if the vision
음, 만약 당신이 믿는 미래의 비전이
of the future that you believe is true,
사실이라면,
and this is going to be an institution
그리고 이것이 한 세기 동안 지속되는
that, that lasts for a century, like what
기관이 될 거라면,
does A16Z look like and do a century
지금으로부터 100년 뒤의 A16Z는 어떤 모습이고 무엇을
to now?
하고 있을까요?
Right.
그렇죠.
Yeah.
네.
So I'll start with, I believe I was
그럼 먼저 말씀드리면, 저는 제가
misquoted.
오해 인용됐다고 생각합니다.
I believe it was a, it was one
제 기억으로는 그게, 그게 이런
of these, uh, hypothetical, uh, thought experiment things
가정적인 사고실험 같은 것들 중 하나였는데요,
that, uh, kind of got, got, uh, overly,
그게 좀, 좀 지나치게
um, extrapolated, but, uh, I, I guess I
음, 확대 해석됐던 것 같습니다만, 음, 저는
shouldn't just, uh, defend myself.
그저 제 자신을 변호만 해서는 안 되겠네요.
Um, so I, the, the, the, the point
음, 그래서 제가 말씀드리려던 요지는
of what I was trying to get across
그 논의에서 전달하려던
in that discussion, um, which we, you know,
핵심인데요, 음, 아시다시피
I think if you both the original, it's,
두 분이 원본을 보시면, 그건
it's a longer form discussion on it.
그에 대한 더 긴 형식의 논의입니다.
It is, goes back to what, what Ben
그것은 벤이
said early on, which is there is this
초반에 말씀하신 내용으로 되돌아가는데, 즉
repeating pattern in history.
역사에는 반복되는 패턴이 있다는 것입니다.
I mean, we, we can find examples of
그러니까요, 저희는 그 사례를
it for sure going back 500 years.
확실히 500년 전까지 거슬러 올라가도 찾을 수 있습니다.
Um, uh, is this repeating pattern, which is
음, 그러니까 그 반복 패턴이란
basically a person with a dream.
기본적으로 꿈을 가진 한 사람입니다.
Um, a person with a deep level of
음, 아주 깊은 수준의
domain knowledge, um, and a dream, um, operating
도메인 지식과 꿈을 가진 사람이, 음, 활동하면서
in a domain with asymmetric payoff, um, right,
비대칭적 보상이 있는 분야에서 말입니다, 음, 그렇죠,
with, with risk and reward, where, you know,
즉 위험과 보상이 있는 곳에서요, 아시다시피,
by the way, the, the dream may be
참고로 그 꿈은
wrong.
틀릴 수도 있습니다.
Like they, they may not be able to
그러니까 그들이 그 일을
do the thing.
해내지 못할 수도 있습니다.
Um, but if they can do the thing,
음, 하지만 그 일을 해낼 수 있다면,
it will, it will have disproportionately high returns.
그건 불균형적으로 높은 수익을 가져오게 됩니다.
Um, you know, the traditional institutional, you know,
음, 아시다시피 전통적인 제도권 기관들, 그러니까
places people go to get support and funding,
사람들이 지원과 자금을 받으러 가는 곳들은
you know, for the dream, you know, for,
그 꿈을 위해서, 그러니까
for, for, for new projects, just turn it
새 프로젝트를 위해서는 그냥
down because, you know, a bank can't finance,
거절해 버리는데, 아시다시피 은행은 자금을 댈 수 없고,
you know, a bank, a bank can't issue
아시다시피 은행은, 은행은
a loan against something with a 50%, you
50% 확률로
know, 50% chance of a 10 accident,
50% 확률로 10배의 성과가 나고,
50% chance of failure.
50% 확률로 실패하는 것에 대해서는요.
Like a bank just can't underwrite that.
은행은 그런 것을 도저히 심사해 줄 수가 없습니다.
So a bank won't do that.
그래서 은행은 그런 일을 하지 않습니다.
Big companies, you know, for the most part,
대기업들도, 대체로는,
won't do that.
그런 일을 하지 않습니다.
Um, uh, you know, almost nobody will do
음, 그러니까 거의 아무도
Um, but, but somebody has a dream and
음, 하지만 누군가는 꿈을 가지고 있고,
then, you know, when the dream works and
그리고 아시다시피 그 꿈이 실현되고,
especially if you can construct a portfolio of
특히 그런 꿈들과 그런 사람들로
those dreams and of those people, you know,
포트폴리오를 구성할 수 있다면,
then the expected, you know, value on that
그에 대한 기대가치가
is, is going to be very high.
매우 높아지게 됩니다.
Like, like that's a very special thing.
그러니까 그건 매우 특별한 일입니다.
Um, I, I've had long conversations with Tyler
음, 저는 타일러 코언과
Cohen, who's very, particularly is very thoughtful on
이 주제에 대해 특히 매우 사려 깊은 사람인데요,
this.
긴 대화를 나눈 적이 있습니다.
And he has a term, forget the exact
그분이 쓰는 용어가 있는데, 정확한
term that he is, it's like, it's, it's
표현은 잊어버렸지만, 그러니까, 그러니까
like some combination talent picker, project picker.
인재를 고르고 프로젝트를 고르는 역할의 조합 같은 것입니다.
Um, and it's, it's this thing, you know,
음, 그리고 그게, 그게 이런 것인데요,
it's like, we were talking about earlier about
아까 시장 규모에 대해 이야기했던 것처럼,
market size.
시장 규모 말입니다.
It's this thing where like, there is an
이건 말하자면,
analytical scientific component to it, but there's also
분석적이고 과학적인 요소도 있지만,
like an art to it.
그와 동시에 일종의 예술적인 면도 있습니다.
And there's, there, there's some intangible cause you're,
그리고, 그러니까, 무형의 요소도 있는데, 왜냐하면 당신은,
you're dealing with human beings at a very
아주
kind of primordial level, you know, kind of,
원초적인 수준에서 인간을 상대하고 있기 때문입니다만,
you know, kind of very early in the
아시다시피 그 과정의 아주 초반에서,
process of doing something that hasn't been done
전에 한 번도 해 본 적 없는 일을 해내는,
before.
그 과정이기 때문입니다.
Um, and, you know, quite honestly, like, you
음, 그리고, 솔직히 말해서, 그러니까,
know, an early example of this was, you
이런 것의 초기 사례로는,
know, Queen Isabella with Christopher Columbus.
이사벨라 여왕과 크리스토퍼 콜럼버스가 있습니다.
Right.
그렇습니다.
Um, and I, I was just like, I
음, 그리고 저는, 그러니까 저는
was just, I was trying to picture the
그 상황에서의 제안을
pitch.
상상해 보려고 했습니다.
Right.
그렇습니다.
You know, Christopher Columbus rolls in.
아시다시피 크리스토퍼 콜럼버스가 들어옵니다.
And he's like, you know, all right, you
그리고 그는 말하죠, 자,
know, here's, you know, I'm going to find
그러니까, 저는 새로운 항로를 찾을 겁니다,
a new route, you know, route to India,
인도로 가는 새로운 항로를요,
by the way.
참고로요.
You know, there's like a, I don't know,
그리고 뭐, 잘 모르겠지만,
whatever 50, 60% chance that, you know,
대충 50%나 60% 정도 확률로,
you'll never hear from me again.
다시는 제 소식을 못 들을 수도 있습니다.
Um, and you know, you know, maybe, you
음, 그리고 어쩌면,
know, maybe, maybe I've, you know, died 2000
어쩌면 저는, 그러니까, 스페인에서 2,000마일 떨어진 곳에서
miles away from Spain.
죽었을 수도 있습니다.
Maybe I may, by the way, maybe I
또 참고로, 어쩌면 저는
just like ran away with the money.
그냥 돈을 들고 도망쳤을 수도 있습니다.
It's not like they had Interpol in those
그 시절에 인터폴 같은 게 있었던 것도 아니고,
days.
그랬던 시대였습니다.
Yeah.
네.
Um, and I'm going to go do that.
음, 저는 그 일을 하러 가겠습니다.
And then, and by the way, the, the
그리고, 또 참고로, 그, 그
fact that that bet paid off, but like,
내기가 결과적으로는 성공했다는 사실은 있지만,
that, that, that, that, like.
그런데, 그러니까, 그게, 그게, 그게 말이죠,
The whole, the whole idea was wrong.
애초의 전체 구상은 틀렸습니다.
Yeah.
네.
But the whole, the whole idea was wrong.
하지만 애초의 전체 구상은 틀렸습니다.
The whole idea was wrong.
전체 구상이 틀렸습니다.
He discovered a completely different continent.
그는 완전히 다른 대륙을 발견했습니다.
And he himself did not believe that he
그리고 그 자신도 자신이
had discovered a completely different continent.
완전히 다른 대륙을 발견했다고 믿지 않았습니다.
Right.
그렇습니다.
Um, and I don't even know that Spain
음, 그리고 저는 스페인이
was the main beneficiary of that in the
그 일의 주요 수혜자였는지도 모르겠습니다,
long run.
장기적으로 말입니다.
Right.
그렇습니다.
Like, and so like, but like, you know,
그러니까, 그래서, 하지만, 아시다시피,
like she funded it and like, wow.
그녀가 그걸 후원했고, 와, 놀랍습니다.
Right.
그렇습니다.
Yeah.
네.
And then there's, there's a lot of gold.
그리고 그다음에는 금이 정말 많이 있었습니다.
Yeah, exactly.
네, 맞습니다.
Yes.
네.
They, they did, they did find some gold.
실제로 금을 좀 찾기는 했습니다.
They're very similar story, by the way.
참고로, 아주 비슷한 이야기입니다.
The Puritans have a, you know, the Plymouth
청교도들도, 아시다시피, 플리머스
Rock, the, that whole thing, the Mayflower, they
록, 그러니까 그 모든 이야기, 메이플라워호도
have a very similar story, uh, to that.
그와 매우 비슷한 이야기가 있습니다.
It took, I think 20 years to raise
자금을 모으는 데, 제 기억으로는, 20년이 걸렸습니다.
the financing, uh, to be able to make
그 원정을 가능하게 할 자금을, 그러니까,
the, uh, make the Mayflower
메이플라워호
Expedition.
원정을 추진하기 위해서였습니다.
Um, and they needed, they needed, you know,
음, 그리고 그들에게는, 아시다시피,
backers like that.
그런 후원자들이 필요했습니다.
You know, that we, we always talk now
우리가 지금도 늘 이야기하듯이
about in the venture industry, you know, the
벤처 업계에서 말하는, 아시다시피, 그
whaling
포경
industry 400 years ago, um, you know, operated
산업이 400년 전에도, 음, 운영 방식이
in a very similar way.
매우 비슷했습니다.
The, the movie industry has always worked this
영화 산업도 늘 이런 방식으로 작동해 왔습니다.
way.
그렇습니다.
The book publishing industry has always worked this
출판 산업도 늘 이런 방식으로 작동해 왔습니다.
By the way, politics has always, you know,
참고로 정치도 늘, 아시다시피,
worked, political campaigns work this way that,
이런 식으로 작동해 왔고, 정치 캠페인도 이런 방식으로 진행되는데,
you know, any, any, any new, you know,
아시다시피 어떤, 어떤, 어떤 새로운, 그러니까,
future president starts out as a long shot,
미래의 대통령이 될 사람도 처음에는 승산이 낮은 후보로 시작하고,
somebody bets on them.
누군가가 그에게 베팅합니다.
And so there's, there's this intangible that has
그래서 이런 무형의 요소가 있는데, 이는
to do with making, making these long dated
아주 장기적인 내기를 하는 것과 관련이 있고,
bets
그런
with very uncertain outcomes and with high failure
결과가 매우 불확실하고 실패율이 높은
rates.
그런 내기입니다.
And I mean, like if, yes, like I
그리고 제 말은, 그렇습니다, 그러니까 저는
think what I said in the original interview
원래 인터뷰에서 제가 말했던 것은,
is like,
그러니까,
look, if we're gonna have AI do that,
보세요, AI가 그 일을 하게 된다면,
like, God bless, like, I'm gonna, like, I'm
정말 신의 가호가 있기를 바랄 일이고, 저는, 그러니까 저는
gonna
그냥
hit the beach and like, it's all good.
해변에 가서 쉬면 되고, 다 괜찮습니다.
Um, but you know, uh, like, I, I
음, 하지만 아시다시피, 그러니까 저는
guess maybe make the following claim and see,
아마 다음과 같은 주장을 해 보고, 그리고
Ben, what
벤, 당신이
you think of this, the intangibles seem to
이것에 대해 어떻게 생각하는지 보고 싶습니다만, 무형의 요소가
be becoming more important, not less important
시간이 지날수록 덜 중요해지는 게 아니라 더 중요해지는 것처럼 보입니다.
over time.
시간이 지날수록 말입니다.
Um, it seems to be becoming more like
음, 점점 더
an art and less like a science as
과학이라기보다 예술에 가까워지는 것 같습니다,
we go.
시간이 갈수록입니다.
Would you agree with that?
이에 동의하십니까?
I, I definitely think that's right because, uh,
저는 분명히 그렇다고 생각합니다, 왜냐하면, 음,
history, um,
역사는, 음,
is a bad guide.
좋은 길잡이가 아니기 때문입니다.
Uh, so you can't like the, the, the,
그러니까 그렇게 할 수는 없습니다, 그, 그, 그,
the interesting thing about VC for me, probably
저에게 VC에서 흥미로운 점은 아마도
the biggest
가장 큰
lesson is you gotta be very careful about
교훈이, 특히 조심해야 할 것은
a highly trained neural net.
고도로 훈련된 신경망이라는 점입니다.
Um, because that's when you make the mistakes
음, 왜냐하면 그럴 때 실수를 하게 되기 때문이고,
because things change.
상황이 변하기 때문입니다.
And I would say things have changed more
그리고 저는 변화가 더
rapidly.
빠르게 일어났다고 말하겠습니다.
Like the thing that we never thought would
예를 들어 우리가 결코 사라지지 않을 거라고
ever, ever, ever go away is the mythical
절대, 절대, 절대 생각했던 것은 바로 '신화적'
man month.
'맨먼스'였습니다.
Um, you know, nine women can't have a
아시다시피 여성 아홉 명이 한 달 만에
baby in a month.
아기를 낳을 수는 없습니다.
Well, with AI, you can, um, you know,
그런데 AI로는 가능할 수도 있습니다, 음, 아시다시피,
with software, it's a metaphor for software.
소프트웨어에서는 그게 소프트웨어에 대한 은유입니다.
It's a metaphor for software.
소프트웨어에 대한 은유입니다.
Yes, exactly.
네, 맞습니다.
Sorry, sorry, sorry.
죄송합니다, 죄송합니다, 죄송합니다.
Uh, so in the old days, right?
그러니까 예전에는, 그렇지 않습니까?
Like no matter how many engineers you put
팀에 엔지니어를 얼마나 많이 투입하든
on a team, you still, you know, more
여전히, 아시다시피, 더 많은
engineers
엔지니어가
would actually slow down the project as opposed
오히려 프로젝트를 느리게 만들었고,
to speed it up.
속도를 높이는 게 아니었습니다.
But now, uh, so you couldn't throw money
하지만 그 당시에는, 그러니까, 돈을
at a problem.
문제에 쏟아붓는 것으로는 해결할 수 없었습니다.
You couldn't throw money at somebody's technological lead.
누군가의 기술적 우위에 돈을 쏟아붓는 것도 불가능했습니다.
You'd have to do something different.
다른 무언가를 해야 했습니다.
Um, now you can throw money at it.
음, 하지만 이제는 돈을 쏟아부을 수 있습니다.
Uh, uh, you know, Elon did an amazing
어, 어, 아시다시피 일론은 놀라울 정도로
job of throwing money, um, at the foundation
돈을, 음, 기초
model
모델
problem and he caught up very, very fast.
문제에 쏟아붓는 일을 해냈고, 아주 아주 빠르게 따라잡았습니다.
And that's something that in the whole history
그리고 그건 우리 업계의 전체 역사에서
of our industry could never have happened before.
이전에는 결코 일어날 수 없었던 일입니다.
So if you had asked an AI, if
그래서 만약 AI에게 물었다면, 만약
Elon had any prayer of catching, um, open
일론이, 음, 따라잡을 가망이 조금이라도 있느냐고, 오픈
AI or anthropic,
AI나 앤스로픽을
they would have said no way.
따라잡을 수 있느냐고요, AI는 절대 아니라고 했을 것입니다.
Uh, and so that's where you're getting into.
음, 그래서 바로 그 지점으로 들어가게 됩니다.
Um, I mean, maybe if the AI was
음, 제 말은, AI가
smart enough, I suppose, but like there, there
충분히 똑똑하다면 가능하다고 할 수도 있지만, 그러니까 그, 그
are these,
런 요소들이 있습니다,
a lot of it has to do with
그중 많은 부분은
like, how much do you believe in the
그 사람을 얼마나 믿느냐와
person?
관련이 있습니다.
Yeah.
네.
And then, and then the other part is
그리고 또 다른 부분은, 우리가 이미 이야기한 것이지만,
what we talked about already, but it's, it's
바로
the long and twisting path.
길고 구불구불한 여정입니다.
You know, the investment's just the beginning.
아시다시피 투자는 시작일 뿐입니다.
Right.
그렇습니다.
And it's the long and twisting path that
그리고 그 길고 구불구불한 여정은
that person and that company take over time,
그 사람과 그 회사가 시간이 지나며 걸어가는 길이고,
um,
음,
and all the different ways that we, you
또 우리가, 아시다시피, 그들을 성공시키기 위해
know, we try to try to try to
계속, 계속, 계속
help them succeed.
도우려고 하는 모든 다양한 방식들입니다.
And so I, I think that, yeah, I,
그래서 저는, 네, 저는,
yeah, if yes, I, I don't know how
네, 그렇다면 저는 어떻게 해야 할지 잘 모르겠습니다.
to have AI do all that.
AI가 그 모든 것을 하게 만드는 방법 말입니다.
Um, but maybe we'll figure it out.
음, 하지만 아마 방법을 찾아낼 수 있을 것입니다.
Yeah.
네.
Uh, you, you could imagine an AI who
어, 모든 걸 할 수 있는 AI를 상상해 볼 수도 있습니다.
could do it all.
그 AI가 모든 것을 해낼 수도 있다는 말입니다.
Of course, if an AI was smart about
물론 AI가 인간 심리를 포함해 모든 것에 대해 똑똑하다면 말입니다.
every single thing, including human psychology, then certainly.
그렇다면 확실히 가능할 것입니다.
Could be.
그럴 수도 있습니다.
You're, you're, you're tasked with training this AI.
당신은, 당신은, 이 AI를 훈련시키는 임무를 맡고 있습니다.
Like what are the things that you've learned
그러면 이 기술에서 당신이 배운 것들 가운데
on this art that you can put into
말로 표현할 수 있는 것은
words?
무엇입니까?
Like if it is, and this is the
만약 그렇다면, 그리고 이것은 제가
most optimistic view of the future I can
미래에 대해 생각할 수 있는 가장 낙관적인 관점인데,
think of, the tools
도구들은
are getting better, but the human piece really,
점점 좋아지고 있지만, 인간적인 요소가 정말,
really matters.
정말 중요합니다.
Like what have you learned about the art
그러면 이 기술에 대해 당신이 배운 것들 중
that you can, that you can describe?
설명할 수 있는 것은 무엇입니까?
Like, what do you look for in, in
예를 들어 '크리스토퍼 콜럼버스' 같은 인물에게서
a Christopher Columbus?
무엇을 찾으십니까?
Well, I mean, I think that, um, the
글쎄요, 제 생각에는, 음, 우선
first thing, and I, you know, I hesitate
첫 번째는, 그리고 아시다시피 저는
to, to name things
이런 것들을 이름 붙이는 데
in, in some sense, cause they're also different,
조금 주저하는데, 어떤 의미에서는 다들 또 다르기 때문입니다,
right?
그렇지요?
Like Elon is really not at all.
예를 들어 일론은 전혀
Like, uh, Mark Zuckerberg.
마크 저커버그와 같지 않고,
Who's not at all.
마크 저커버그도 전혀
Like Ali Goetze.
알리 괴츠와 같지 않으며,
Who's not like at all.
알리 괴츠도 전혀
Like Brian Chesky.
브라이언 체스키와 같지 않습니다.
So like, like they're all different.
그러니까, 다들 다릅니다.
Um, and the, but the things that they
음, 그리고, 하지만 그들이
all do, I would say is, um, they
공통으로 하는 것이라면, 음,
all think for themselves.
모두 스스로 생각한다는 점입니다.
They're not people who read the room and
그들은 분위기를 읽고
try and like figure out what people want
사람들이 자신에게 무엇을
them to
원하는지
do.
알아내서 그에 맞추려는 사람이 아닙니다.
They, they, they have original ideas.
그들은, 그들은, 독창적인 아이디어를 갖고 있습니다.
So original idea is probably the thing that
그래서 독창적인 아이디어가 아마도
every great entrepreneur has their original
모든 위대한 기업가가 갖추고 있는 것이고,
thinkers.
그들은 독창적인 사상가들입니다.
Um, and then, you know, they, they all
음, 그리고 또 아시다시피, 그들은 모두
also have some combination of enough charisma.
충분한 카리스마를 어느 정도 갖추고 있습니다.
They're interesting enough, um, that people want to
사람들이 따르고 싶어 할 만큼 충분히 흥미롭고,
follow them.
그래서 사람들이 그들을 따르고 싶어 합니다.
Um, because, you know, ultimately you, you kind
음, 왜냐하면 아시다시피 결국에는
of need people to go, okay, that is
사람들이 '좋아, 저 사람이 리더다'라고
the leader.
생각해야 하기 때문입니다.
And that's somebody who I want to work
그리고 '저 사람과 함께 일하고 싶고'
with, work for, and so forth.
'저 사람 밑에서 일하고 싶다'고 생각해야 합니다.
Uh, so that's, those are the things that
어, 그래서 그게 제가 말하자면 거의 모든 사람이 갖고 있는 것들입니다.
I would say almost all of them have.
그리고 저는
And then, and I think all of them
위대해지려면 모두
have those to be great.
그것들을 갖춰야 한다고 생각합니다.
Uh, but everything else, I, you know, like
어, 하지만 그 밖의 모든 것은, 아시다시피,
Steve Jobs is a very different kind of
스티브 잡스는 정말 완전히 다른 유형의 사람입니다.
guy.
말 그대로요.
Um, they're all, they're all different.
음, 다들, 다들 다릅니다.
I would say very, like Steve Jobs, nothing
이를테면 스티브 잡스는
like Andy Grove, like nothing.
앤디 그로브와는 전혀 다릅니다, 전혀요.
Uh, but you know, they're both great.
어, 하지만 아시다시피 둘 다 훌륭합니다.
To close this out, I guess, from, from
마무리하면서, 그러니까, 두 분께
each of you, what is the thing that
각자 묻고 싶은데,
you're personally
개인적으로
most excited about in the next kind of
앞으로
couple of years of a 16 Z, but
향후 몇 년간 a16z에서, 그리고
just tech more broadly?
더 넓게는 기술 전반에서 가장 기대되는 것은 무엇입니까?
Well, I mean, I mean, you know, you
글쎄요, 제 말은, 그러니까, 아시다시피
know, Mark, Mark had a great line.
마크가 정말 좋은 표현을 했습니다.
Like, well, this is on the order of
예를 들어 이것은
like the steam engine or electricity or like,
증기기관이나 전기 같은 것과 비슷한 수준의,
like this
그러니까
is such a big invention, um, that we're
너무나 거대한 발명이라서, 음, 우리가
gonna end up in a different world.
결국 전혀 다른 세계에 살게 될 것이라는 말이었습니다.
And the thing that's most exciting to me
그리고 이에 대해 제게 가장 설레는 점은
about it is, you know, I, I wouldn't
아시다시피, 저는
want to live
살고 싶지 않습니다,
in the pre-electricity world.
전기가 없던 시대에는요.
Um, like I like this world way, way,
음, 저는 지금의 이 세상이 훨씬, 훨씬,
way better.
훨씬 더 좋습니다.
And so I think that like odds are,
그래서 제 생각에는 아마
we're gonna get to a world that's just
우리는
way, way better than
지금보다 훨씬, 훨씬 더 나은 세계에
we can even like, we can't even get
도달하게 될 것이고, 그러니까
our heads around it, which is why it
우리의 머리로조차 다 이해할 수 없을 정도여서,
freaks people out.
그래서 사람들이 겁을 내는 것입니다.
Like all these stuff that we have to
우리가 해야 하는 온갖 일들,
do and so forth that we've just learned
그리고 기타 등등, 우리가 그저 익숙해져 버린 것들,
to live with that sucks,
하지만 사실은 형편없는 것들 말입니다,
um, isn't gonna be required anymore.
음, 그런 것들이 더는 필요하지 않게 될 것입니다.
And so like, you know, what does that
그래서 아시다시피, 그게 무슨 뜻일까요?
mean?
그게 무슨 의미일까요?
What do we think of them?
우리는 그것을 어떻게 생각하게 될까요?
Like what is life become?
삶은 무엇이 되어 갈까요?
It could be, uh, you know, super exciting.
어, 아시다시피 정말 엄청나게 흥미로울 수도 있습니다.
Now, the one thing with humans, that's a
다만 인간에 관해 한 가지 조금 꼬인 점이 있는데,
little messed up is, you know, if that
아시다시피 만약 그런 변화가
takes us too far away,
우리를 너무 멀리 데려가서,
like one of the, you know, too far
즉 아시다시피 어떤 현실적인 목적에서 너무 멀어지게 된다면,
away from some grounded purpose, uh, about, um,
어, 그러니까, 음,
you know, and
아시다시피, 그리고
beliefs, uh, and spirituality, then, you know, you
신념이라든지, 어, 영성 같은 것에서 멀어지면,
can attach on to some dumb stuff.
아시다시피 사람들이 어떤 어리석은 것들에 집착할 수도 있습니다.
Uh, so, you know, that, that, that would
어, 그래서 아시다시피, 그게, 그게, 그게 사실 제 유일한 걱정입니다만,
be actually my only worry, but I think
저는
life just
삶이, 그러니까
the quality of life for everybody's about to
모든 사람의 삶의 질이
get like way, way better than it's ever
이전 어느 때보다도 훨씬, 훨씬 더
been.
좋아질 것이라고 생각합니다.
I'm excited about the zoomers.
저는 줌머 세대가 기대됩니다.
I am psyched for the zoomers.
저는 줌머 세대가 정말 기대됩니다.
Um, I was with a, uh, I was
음, 저는 얼마 전
with a, uh, a founder, a founder team
어, 창업자들, 그러니까 창업팀과
the other day.
함께 있었습니다.
Um, and, uh, I was, who are zoomers
음, 그리고, 어, 저는, 그들은 줌머들이었고
and I was explaining to them, you know,
저는 그들에게 아시다시피
why the zoomers are so much better than
왜 줌머가 밀레니얼보다 훨씬 낫고
the millennials and why they're gonna save us.
왜 그들이 우리를 구할 것이며
And like, the whole thing is gonna be
그리고 모든 게
great.
정말 좋아질 거라고 설명하고 있었습니다.
This is so great.
정말 대단하다고요.
And of course, they're just like staring at
그런데 물론 그들은 마치
me, like I'm speaking Greek because like they
제가 그리스어로 말하는 것처럼 저를 바라봤습니다, 왜냐하면
did, you know, they're, you know, they're, you
아시다시피 그들은
know, they just think like millennials are like
그러니까, 그들은 밀레니얼을 그냥
old farts that are like completely out of
완전히 시대에 뒤떨어진 늙은이들이라고
touch.
생각합니다.
Um, and of course, you know, us, Ben
음, 그리고 물론 아시다시피 저희, 벤
and I are Gen Xers, we might as
그리고 저는 X세대라서, 어쩌면
well be, you know, Stone Age.
석기시대 사람이나 다름없습니다.
Um, and, and I was like, but I
음, 그래서 저는, 저는 이렇게 말했는데요, 하지만
was like, but I was like, this is
제가 말하길, 제가 말하길, 이게 바로
what's so great about the zoomers.
Z세대의 정말 좋은 점입니다.
Like they just like, they're, they're, it's, it's
그러니까 이들은 그냥, 이들은, 이건
the, it's the post that I would describe
제가 표현하자면 일종의
it as 2015 to 2024 was just, it
2015년부터 2024년까지가 그냥
was a very, very strange period.
아주, 아주 이상한 시기였습니다.
Um, and a lot of just things got
음, 그리고 많은 것들이 그냥
really weird.
정말 이상해졌습니다.
Um, and the zoomers are the generation that
음, 그리고 줌머는 그런 상황을
basically was on the receiving end of that.
사실상 정면으로 겪은 세대입니다.
And I, they're at least for the zoomers
그리고 제가 보기에, 적어도 우리가 만나는 줌머들은
we get to deal with, like, they're just
저희가 상대하게 되는 분들은, 그냥
not having it.
그걸 더는 받아들이지 않습니다.
Um, and they're not walking around feeling guilty
그리고 온종일 모든 것에 죄책감을 느끼며 다니지도 않습니다.
about everything all the time.
항상 모든 일에 죄책감을 느끼지도 않습니다.
They're not feeling like they have to like
성공하고 싶다는 걸
deny that they want to be successful.
부정해야 한다고 느끼지도 않습니다.
You know, they don't have any of the
아시다시피, 그들에게는 그런
moral, you know, kind of hair shirt stuff.
도덕적 자기학대 같은 게 없습니다.
Um, they're, they're just like, they're there.
그냥, 그냥 거기에 있습니다.
If anything, they were like that too.
오히려 그들도 그랬습니다.
Gen X kind of let go of all
X세대는 대체로
the craziness of the sixties and early seventies.
60년대와 70년대 초반의 온갖 광기를 내려놓았습니다.
Yeah, that's right.
네, 맞습니다.
That's right.
맞습니다.
You're right.
말씀 맞습니다.
Exactly.
정확합니다.
Gen X was the reaction of the boomers
X세대는 베이비붐 세대에 대한 반작용이었고
in the same way the zoomers are reaction
줌머는 같은 방식으로 반작용입니다.
to the millennials.
밀레니얼 세대에 대한 반작용이죠.
Um, and so the, the, the zoomer founders
그래서 저희가 상대하게 되는 Z세대 창업자들은
that we get to deal with, I, my
제 관점에서는, 정말
view is like, it's the best, it's the
최고이고, 최고이고,
best, it's the best, most competent, most capable.
가장 유능하고, 가장 역량이 뛰어납니다.
By the way, they're just like incredibly well,
그리고 덧붙이자면, 이들은 정말 믿기지 않을 만큼
they come in all just incredibly well trained
정말 믿기지 않을 만큼 잘 훈련되어 있고
and indicated because they grew up online.
온라인에서 자라서 준비가 되어 있습니다.
You know, they've seen, you know, a thousand
아시다시피, 이들은
hours of YouTube videos from all the great,
유튜브에서 훌륭한 기술 업계 사람들의 영상
you know, people in tech talking about how
천 시간 분량을 보며
to do everything.
모든 것을 어떻게 하는지 배웠습니다.
You know, they just know so much more
그러니까 이들은 그냥 훨씬 더 많이 알고 있습니다.
than previous generations of founders did.
이전 세대의 창업자들보다 훨씬 더 많이요.
Um, and you know, they're, by the way,
그리고 아시다시피, 덧붙이자면
they're, now they're all AI native.
이제는 다들 AI 네이티브입니다.
Um, you know, they all, you know, basically
그러니까, 이들은 다들 기본적으로
learned AI from scratch and, you know, in
AI를 처음부터 배웠고, 아시다시피
college and, you know, they're coming out and
대학에서요, 그리고 나와서
they, they totally understand it.
그걸 완전히 이해하고 있습니다.
Um, and so, and they're just like tremendously
그리고 그래서, 이들은 정말 엄청나게
fired up and like completely, you know, completely,
의욕에 불타 있고, 완전히, 아시다시피 완전히,
you know, they wear their, you know, they
아시다시피, 마음을 숨기지 않습니다.
wear the heart on their sleeve.
속마음을 그대로 드러냅니다.
They're like, they're, they're gonna build something, they're
이들은 뭔가를 만들 겁니다, 뭔가를 만들 겁니다, 정말
gonna build something great.
위대한 것을 만들 겁니다.
And they're completely unapologetic about it.
그리고 그걸 전혀 미안해하지도 않습니다.
Uh, they're very forceful.
아주 강하게 밀어붙입니다.
They're very determined.
아주 단호합니다.
Um, yeah, I, I, I just think it's
그러니까, 저는 정말로 이게
fantastic.
환상적이라고 생각합니다.
I, I've been waiting this bit.
저는 이걸 기다려 왔습니다.
Eric and Ben will tell you, I've been
에릭과 벤이 말해 줄 텐데, 저는
waiting for this, uh, for, for a long
이걸, 그러니까, 정말 오랫동안
time.
기다려 왔습니다.
We may have to edit this out, but
이건 편집해야 할지도 모르지만,
one of the things I do really like
제가 Z세대에서 정말 좋아하는 점 중 하나는
about the Zoomers,
제가 그동안 한 번도
I haven't ever heard anybody say anything like,
누구에게서도 이런 말을 들어본 적이 없다는 겁니다,
I'm gonna do well by doing good.
“좋은 일을 하면서도 잘되겠다” 같은 말이요.
Exactly.
정확합니다.
Like they never fucking say that bullshit.
그러니까 그런 헛소리는 절대 하지 않습니다.
No, no.
아니요, 아니요.
None of that stuff.
그런 건 전혀 없습니다.
And they have a good sense of humor
게다가 유머 감각도 좋습니다.
too.
재미있습니다.
They're funny.
정말 웃깁니다.
Yes.
네.
They're extremely funny.
정말 엄청나게 웃깁니다.
They get, they get it.
핵심을 압니다.
They get, they, they lived through, they were
이들은 겪어 왔습니다, 직접 당해 봤습니다, 이들은
on the receiving end of just a tremendous
엄청난 양의
amount
헛소리를
of bullshit.
직접 당해 봤습니다.
And they're just like, they're just not having
그리고 이들은 그냥, 그런 걸
it.
더는 받아들이지 않습니다.
Um, and so it's just, I find it
그래서 저는 그게 정말 엄청나게
just like tremendously exciting, uh, to, to be
흥분되고, 그러니까, 이렇게
able to
할 수 있다는 게요.
work with them.
그들과 함께 일하는 것이요.
And I, um, I, if, if I, if
그리고 저는, 음, 제가, 제가 만약
I had total control over my time, it
시간을 완전히 통제할 수 있다면
would be a hundred percent.
그게 100%일 겁니다.
That was the worst.
그건 최악이었습니다.
Well, I appreciate you spending an hour with
밀레니얼 한 명과 한 시간을 함께해 주셔서 감사합니다.
a millennial.
정말 재미있었습니다.
This was a ton of fun.
정말 즐거웠습니다.
Thank you for letting me write about, uh,
a16z에 대해 글을 쓸 수 있게 해 주셔서 감사합니다.
about A16Z and thanks for, thanks for the
그리고 대화도, 정말 감사합니다.
conversation.
감사합니다.
We're, we're talking about all your future guests.
우리는 당신의 앞으로의 모든 게스트에 대해 이야기하고 있습니다.
Yeah, exactly.
네, 정확합니다.
Yeah.
네.
Vacci, this was an excellent piece.
패키, 이 글 정말 훌륭했습니다.
Thank you so much for writing.
써 주셔서 정말 감사합니다.
Yeah.
네.
Yes.
100%입니다.
Good.
좋습니다.
Yeah.
네.
You
당신은